<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.4.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-20T16:44:13-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">[“Colton Grainger”]</title><subtitle>[&quot;licensed CC0&quot;]</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Dropping out of Grad School</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dropping-out-of-grad-school" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dropping out of Grad School" /><published>2020-06-20T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-06-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dropping-out-of-grad-school</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dropping-out-of-grad-school">&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 1.5 years in CU Boulder’s math PhD program, I had “too many fish to fry” (a conflagration of conflicting commitments!), and signed papers to take an indefinite leave of absence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m glad to have now discerned that, after all, I won’t go back to the math department (as much as I would love to enroll in classes) on a teaching assistantship, because would rather “&lt;a href=&quot;https://mariedavidson.bandcamp.com/track/work-it&quot;&gt;work to be a winner, baby&lt;/a&gt;” by breaking into the world as a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://candor.co/&quot;&gt;tech professional&lt;/a&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following folks were instrumental in helping me realize that I could (and in fact should) pivot in my career trajectory: Agnès, Richard, Peter, Divya, Sam, JQ, Yu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t really owe anyone an explanation, but since I might later be curious why I’m pivoting, I’ve compiled the following reverse chronological entries from a “working journal” I started in the style of Philip Guo, Issa Rice, and Nadia Egbhal between 0.5 and 2 years’ time in grad school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2020-05-28&quot;&gt;2020-05-28&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a phone interview today with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.crunchbase.com/organization/jelli&quot;&gt;Jelli&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the advice of &lt;a href=&quot;https://candor.co/interview-prep/how-to-not-suck-at-behavioral-interviews&quot;&gt;https://candor.co/interview-prep/how-to-not-suck-at-behavioral-interviews&lt;/a&gt;, I’m preparing answers to the following ten “very basic interview questions that come up all the time”, relative to my application for an entry-level software engineering position at Jelli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2020-04-20&quot;&gt;2020-04-20&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I moved to Boise, Idaho, my hometown, after &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mescaline&quot;&gt;getting the bad idea&lt;/a&gt; to leave Olympia and try to live in Tacoma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2020-03-31&quot;&gt;2020-03-31&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Found out yesterday I didn’t get the NSF
GRF for 2020 (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/coltongrainger/fy20nsf&quot;&gt;application documents&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on this news (rather early in the morning):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think have been avoiding certain life tasks for want of superficial reward.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Had I gotten the GRF, I would’ve leveraged this funding to exacerbate power struggles in my “vertical” relationships (namely avoiding TA duties), rather than building horizontal relationships (what Alder describes as ‘community feeling’).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now, since I am no longer tied to Boulder, I have freedom to choose where I want to live: and I want to live in Houston, TX.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’re sections of texts I read to mull over my (vocational) tasks as distinct from the tasks of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tao-te-ching-lyric-9-translated-by-aleister-crowley&quot;&gt;Tao Te Ching, lyric 9, translated by Aleister Crowley&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Originally quoted to me by Dave Spring 2014 after poorly passing Differential Equations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fill not a vessel, lest it spill in carrying. Meddle not with a sharpened point
by feeling it constantly, or it will soon become blunted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gold and jade endanger the house of their possessor. Wealth and honors lead to
arrogance and envy, and bring ruin. Is they way famous and thy name becoming
distinguished? Withdraw, thy work once done, into obscurity; this is the way of
Heaven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bhagavad-gita-verses-327335-paraphrased-from-edgarton-franklin&quot;&gt;Bhagavad Gita, verses 3.27–3.35, paraphrased from Edgarton Franklin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Material nature’s Strands perform all actions. And one whose soul is deluded by ego imagines: ‘I am the agent behind these actions.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet one who knows the truth, O mighty Arjuna, — ‘The Strands act upon the Strands’ — is not attached to actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bewildered by material nature’s Strands, many attach their Self to these Strands’ actions. But those of complete knowledge cannot disturb these dull folks of incomplete knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Arjuna, surrendering all your activities unto Me, fixing your mind on your highest self, being free from longing and selfishness, cast lethargy aside and fight!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who follow this doctrine of Mine, full of faith and not murmuring, are released from their karma bondage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But those who — murmuring against it —  do not follow my doctrine, are deluded in all their knowledge; know that these fools are lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One acts according to their own material nature — even the wise — as all beings follow their nature; what can repression accomplish?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of every sense, upon the objects of that sense, longing and loathing are fixed. But one should not fall under their power, as both are foes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Better one’s own duty, (tho) imperfect, than another’s duty well performed.
Better death while performing one’s own duty — another’s duty brings danger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-courage-to-be-disliked-page-186-ichiro-kishimi-and-fumitame-koga&quot;&gt;The Courage to Be Disliked, page 186, Ichiro Kishimi and Fumitame Koga&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Recommended to me by Scott this last Winter.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Youth: But! When one is praised by another person, one becomes truly aware of
one’s ability and regains one’s courage. Please do not be stubborn about this
point — just acknowledge the necessity of giving praise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philosopher: No, I will not acknowledge that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Youth: Why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philosopher: The reason is clear. Being praised is what leads people to form the
belief that they have no ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Youth: What did you say?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philosopher: Shall I repeat myself? The more one is praised by another, the more
one forms the belief that one has no ability. Please do your best to remember
this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Youth: Do such foolish people even exist? It’s got to be the other way around!
It is as a result of being praised that one becomes truly aware of one’s
ability: isn’t that obvious?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philosopher: You are wrong. Even if you do derive joy from being praised, it is
the same as being dependent on relationships to your perceived superiors, and
implicitly conceding that you have no ability. Because giving praise is a
judgement that is passed by a person of ability onto a person without.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Youth: I just cannot agree with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philosopher: When receiving praise becomes one’s goal, one is choosing a way of
living that is in line with another person’s system of values. Looking at your
life until now, aren’t you tired of trying to live up to your superior’s
expectations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Youth: Um, well, I guess so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philosopher: First, do the separation of tasks. Then, while accepting each
other’s difference, build equal horizontal relationships. Encouragement is the
approach that comes next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Youth: So, concretely speaking, how does one go about this? One cannot praise,
and one cannot rebuke. What other words and choices are there?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2020-03-17&quot;&gt;2020-03-17&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy belated Pi Day! I have spent the last month or so learning how to “write idiomatic python programs” by studying notes from Jake Vanderplas [@Van16], Wes McKinney [@McK17], Michael Eichberg [@Eic18], John Guttag [@Gut16], and others [@Sha17]. Here’s a bibliography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;project-development&quot;&gt;Project Development&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A summary of [@Eic18].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The goal [of these notes] is to enable you to systematically carry out small(er) commercial or open-source software projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Basic knowledge of object-oriented programming concepts is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A summary of [@Sha17].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Just write down what you think your process is and
what problems you seem to have. At this stage you might have no idea how you
work because you aren’t very experienced. To help you I’ve compiled a list of
questions:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Do you tend to make defective code with no idea why?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Do you keep piling code on top of code until there’s just a huge mess?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Do you get past the first implementation of your project and have no idea how to take it further?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Do you feel inferior or like a fraud who will get caught?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;idiomatic-python&quot;&gt;“Idiomatic” Python&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A summary of [@Gut16].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When you have finished this book you should have […] learned a systematic approach to &lt;em&gt;organizing, writing, and debugging medium-sized programs&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A summary of [@Van16].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Whirlwind Tour of Python&lt;/em&gt; is a fast-paced introduction to &lt;em&gt;essential features [e.g., errors and exceptions, modules and packages]&lt;/em&gt; of the Python language, aimed at researchers and developers who are already familiar with programming in another language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A summary of [@McK17].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This book is concerned with the nuts and bolts of &lt;em&gt;manipulating, processing, cleaning,
and crunching data in Python.&lt;/em&gt; My goal is to offer a guide to the parts of the Python
programming language and its data-oriented library ecosystem and tools that will
equip you to become an effective data analyst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pythonic-sql&quot;&gt;“Pythonic” SQL&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the introduction to [@Cop15].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;SQL is a powerful language for querying and manipulating data in a database,
but sometimes it’s tough to integrate it with the rest of your application.
You may have used string manipulation to generate queries to run over an
ODBC interface, or used a DB API as a Python programmer. While those can be
effective ways to handle data, they can make security and database changes
very difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This book is about a very powerful and flexible Python library named
SQLAlchemy that bridges the gap between relational databases and traditional
programming. While SQLAlchemy allows you to “drop down” into raw SQL to
execute your queries, it encourages higher-level thinking through a more
“Pythonic” and friendly approach to database queries and updates. It
supplies the tools that let you map your application’s classes and objects
to database tables once and then to “forget about it,” or to return to
your model again and again to fine-tune performance.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;SQLAlchemy is powerful and flexible, but it can also be a little daunting.
SQLAlchemy tutorials expose only a fraction of what’s available in this
excellent library, and though the online documentation is extensive, it is
often better as a reference than as a way to learn the library initially. This
book is meant as a learning tool and a handy reference for when you’re in
“implementation mode” and need an answer fast.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This book is intended for those who want to learn more about how to use relational
databases in their Python programs, or have heard about SQLAlchemy and want
more information on it. To get the most out of this book, the reader should have
intermediate Python skills and at least moderate exposure to SQL databases. […] If you are new to SQL and databases, check out &lt;em&gt;Learning SQL&lt;/em&gt; by Alan
Beaulieu [@Bea20]. These will fill in any missing gaps as you work through this book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2020-02-05&quot;&gt;2020-02-05&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MWE for the image archive. &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.coltongrainger.com/attached/2020-02-05-mwe.tar.gz&quot;&gt;https://blog.coltongrainger.com/attached/2020-02-05-mwe.tar.gz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2020-01-21&quot;&gt;2020-01-21&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ncar_pylib&lt;/code&gt;, there’s no module &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;MySQLdb&lt;/code&gt; nor module &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pymysql&lt;/code&gt;. But SQLAlchemy can still connect via the connection string (c.f. &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.sqlalchemy.org/en/13/dialects/mysql.html#module-sqlalchemy.dialects.mysql.mysqlconnector&quot;&gt;https://docs.sqlalchemy.org/en/13/dialects/mysql.html#module-sqlalchemy.dialects.mysql.mysqlconnector&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mysql+mysqlconnector://&amp;lt;user&amp;gt;:&amp;lt;password&amp;gt;@&amp;lt;host&amp;gt;[:&amp;lt;port&amp;gt;]/&amp;lt;dbname&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;through &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mysql-connector&lt;/code&gt;, which &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2020-01-20&quot;&gt;2020-01-20&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;B-tree&lt;/code&gt; indexes and in group theory, a “transversal” refers to a unique set of “class” representatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ad. L. transvers-us turned or directed across, pa. pple. of transvertĕre: see
transvert. Cf. F. transverse (16th c.).]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2020-01-18&quot;&gt;2020-01-18&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found Philip’s sample images on the SIParCS google drive and feel like a straight fool for not knowing they were there. I now have 7.4 GB of raw images to use as a test image database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, I should also include the logbooks of the USS Jeanette.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://research.archives.gov/id/6919191&quot;&gt;https://research.archives.gov/id/6919191&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://research.archives.gov/id/6919192&quot;&gt;https://research.archives.gov/id/6919192&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://research.archives.gov/id/6919193&quot;&gt;https://research.archives.gov/id/6919193&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://research.archives.gov/id/6919194&quot;&gt;https://research.archives.gov/id/6919194&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I’d at least better be able to connect to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rda-db.ucar.edu
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but I can’t even seem to do this with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;globalprotect connect --portal gp.ucar.edu
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erg! But there’s hope, if I shell into Casper first (or maybe just use my work laptop) then I can access&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mysql -h rda-db.ucar.edu -u &amp;lt;user&amp;gt; -p&amp;lt;password&amp;gt; images 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;with no problem. Moreover&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;MySQL [images]&amp;gt; show grants for dssdb@localhost;

GRANT ALL PRIVILEGES ON `images`.* TO 'dssdb'@'localhost'
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;so that if I create the user &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;dssdb&lt;/code&gt; on my local mysql server, and am able to inject metadata there, porting over to Casper shouldn’t be too difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have through MLK day to do it. Yikes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;-bash-4.2$ mysql -h rda-db.ucar.edu -u dssdb -p -V
mysql  Ver 15.1 Distrib 5.5.56-MariaDB, for Linux (x86_64) using readline 5.1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2020-01-17&quot;&gt;2020-01-17&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I need for yoga during the next couple of months? Christina lists:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An open mind and a commitment to learning.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A journal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A notebook and pen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A good mat, a mat towel.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Layers and clean clothing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eating utensils, snacks, packed lunches.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consider dropping or reducing caffeine, sugar, smoking, social media, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extra support. We encourage other modalities (i.e. therapy, acupuncture, massage, etc.) to complement yoga.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A light heart.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2020-01-13&quot;&gt;2020-01-13&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a bibliography for some “&lt;a href=&quot;attached/1984-iyengar-ymca.jpg&quot;&gt;gymnastics&lt;/a&gt;” that I’m getting into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;1966-iyengar-light-on-yoga
2014-hansen-netters-anatomy-coloring-book
1997-ellis-clinical-anatomy

2002-iyengar-light-on-the-yoga-sutras-of-patanjali
2010-freeman-the-mirror-of-yoga
2009-adele-the-yamas-and-niyamas-exploring-yoga-as-ethical-practice

2000-rothschild-the-body-remembers
2004-naparstek-invisible-heroes
2004-vanderkolk-the-body-keeps-score

2015-rose-untangled
2017-sherman-alexie-you-dont-have-to-say-you-love-me
2006-tharp-the-creative-habit
2012-cope-the-great-work-of-your-life
2000-rothschild-the-body-remembers-casebook

2004-alter-yoga-in-modern-india
2005-de-michelis-elizabeth-history-of-modern-yoga
2010-singleton-yoga-body-the-origins-of-modern-posture-practice
2017-mallinson-singleton-the-roots-of-modern-yoga

2018-cohen-the-upanishads-routeledge
2016-ithamar-exploring-the-bhagavad-gita

2000-snyder-reader-prose-poetry-and-translations
2010-snyder-the-practice-of-the-wild

2000-desalvo-writing-as-a-way-of-healing
2014-snyder-martin-nobody-home-writing-buddhism-and-living-in-places
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2020-01-10&quot;&gt;2020-01-10&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.inechi.com/2019/11/2019.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;attached/2019-03-inechii-introspection.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Inés Estrada, March 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2020-01-04&quot;&gt;2020-01-04&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I might be motivated to work &lt;em&gt;for a particular person&lt;/em&gt; rather than on &lt;em&gt;a specific project&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This style of motivation is appropriate because I’ve given up on logging time for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From my experience with kan-ban and without a cell phone over the last 3 months (since failing two prelims this Fall), I recognize I just shouldn’t &lt;em&gt;actively&lt;/em&gt; track myself when I’m “working on myself”. (I have some &lt;em&gt;passive trackers&lt;/em&gt;, e.g., time series data for my heartrate, my sleep, and my approximate location. But I don’t have to remember do anything to collect this data, and I get to analyze it post hoc.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I &lt;em&gt;would like&lt;/em&gt; to actively track myself, so I’m trying to be attentive (when I’m working) to &lt;em&gt;whom&lt;/em&gt; I feel I am working for, rather than fretting to much about &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; I am doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;chores for myself&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rdai docs for Matt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rdai database for Tom&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;topology notes for Agnès&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;algebra notes for Peter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;analysis notes for Sergei&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2020-01-01&quot;&gt;2020-01-01&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;attached/donuts.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Donuts at the Boise Art Museum with Sam&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this summer with Sam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-11-28&quot;&gt;2019-11-28&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visited my folks in Idaho. Stopped going to classes once I got back to Boulder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-11-07&quot;&gt;2019-11-07&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am working as a student visitor for &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20191221123926/https://staff.ucar.edu/browse/orgs/DECS&quot;&gt;DECS&lt;/a&gt; at NCAR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-10-28&quot;&gt;2019-10-28&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I present on the Research Data Archive’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/coltongrainger/rda-image-archive/&quot;&gt;image repository&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/save/https://www.colorado.edu/csl/steminar/fall-2019-steminar-schedule&quot;&gt;CU STEMinar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-09-24&quot;&gt;2019-09-24&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I present on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.math.harvard.edu/~lurie/252xnotes/Lecture2.pdf&quot;&gt;Lazard’s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.math.harvard.edu/~lurie/252xnotes/Lecture3.pdf&quot;&gt;theorem&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://math.colorado.edu/seminars/?date=2019-09-24&quot;&gt;CU topology seminar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2020-09-01&quot;&gt;2020-09-01&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty sure I failed some prelims. Opps. Quit vaping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-08-25&quot;&gt;2019-08-25&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am teaching &lt;a href=&quot;https://math2510.coltongrainger.com&quot;&gt;Math 2510-001 Introduction to Statistics&lt;/a&gt; this fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-07-31&quot;&gt;2019-07-31&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I present &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wURNDpfBS4Q&quot;&gt;Towards Categorical Metadata&lt;/a&gt; for SIParCS at NCAR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-07-04&quot;&gt;2019-07-04&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth of July BBQ with Janet and the SIParCS cohort. Janet and Ian left town to visit their folks, leaving me alone at 858 9th St for about a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-06-04&quot;&gt;2019-06-04&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I’m liable to forget, I’ll describe my current “PIM schema” by cataloging&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;my &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$HOME&lt;/code&gt; directory,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what I have on paper, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;software I subscribe to for managing projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;home&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$HOME&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a Lenovo T420, whose name is &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lobster&lt;/code&gt;. My home directory looks something like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;colton@lobster:~$ tree -L 1
.
├── art
├── blog
├── coltongrainger.bib
├── cv
├── Dropbox
├── fy
├── journal
├── lec
├── lit
├── mus
├── pho
├── raw
├── README.md
├── rec
├── rote
└── wiki
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During “fiscal year 2019” (i.e., Jun 2018 to May 2019), I commonly worked commonly in&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fy&lt;/code&gt; (projects for the “fiscal year”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;wiki&lt;/code&gt; (materials for &lt;a href=&quot;https://quamash.net&quot;&gt;https://quamash.net&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;raw&lt;/code&gt; (scanned handwritten notes, hence &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;raw&lt;/code&gt;) and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rote&lt;/code&gt; (tab separated files for mnemosyne).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The previous two years (modulo a few details) look like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;colton@lobster:~$ tree -L 1 fy/18
fy/18
├── 2017-09-job-apps
├── 2018-04-16-offer-letter-cu-boulder.pdf
├── 2018-04-27-picklebric-application.txt
├── 2018-06-18-tutoring
├── bulma-0.7.1
├── coding-with-kids
├── cogr-webpage
├── coq
├── data-management-plan
├── diagnostic
├── dishwashing
├── eo
├── fscss-interviews
├── fscss-private
├── fscss-wiki
├── fscss-work
├── grad-apps
├── grad-funding
├── grap-apps.bak
├── hakyll
├── leading-lesson
├── logos
├── mentoring
├── mnep-script
├── notedown
├── num
├── odes
├── PreTeXt-mathbook
├── prob
├── py
├── PythonDataScienceHandbook
├── rcf
├── spoken-word
└── tex-templates
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;colton@lobster:~$ tree -L 1 fy/19
fy/19
├── 2018-06-alg1-top1-ana1.pdf
├── 2018-06-until-2019-02.pdf
├── 2019-03-topology-seminars.pdf
├── 2019-05-11-top2-omnibus.pdf
├── alg1
├── alg2
├── clothing
├── cu3d
├── diffgeo1
├── dircolors-solarized
├── examples
├── internships
├── mitschriebwiki
├── napkin-outline
├── neural-network
├── orientation
├── prelims
├── prob1
├── project-ideas
├── records-and-old-todo
├── ripser
├── RISE
├── safe
├── slow-pitch
├── soml
├── stylefiles
├── summer-review
├── ta
├── TDAstats
├── top1
├── top2
├── tripos-course-guides
├── unicode.sh
├── vim-tex-fold
└── yst
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About 75% of repositories I have on github (for lack of a better name) are prefixed with, e.g., &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fy00&lt;/code&gt;, to indicate that they are locally saved under, e.g., &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$HOME/fy/00/&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only have digital directories under &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fy&lt;/code&gt; back to (about) 2009–2010, when I was spending quite a bit of time after school with “kdawg wangalicous” and the policy debate topic was&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Resolved: The United States federal government should substantially increase social services for persons living in poverty in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;colton@lobster:~/fy/10$ tree
.
├── 2009-apology-to-davidson.txt
├── 2009-GDI-Nietzsche-K.pdf
├── 2009-GDI-Objectivism.pdf
├── 2009-UTNIF-Carceral-Archipelago-K.pdf
├── 2009-UTNIF-Marxism-K.pdf
├── 2009-UTNIF-Standpoint-Epistemology-Critique.pdf
├── 2010-ecopanda-behemoth.pptx
├── 2010-ganatos-nary-slender-script.txt
└── 2010-mein-lieblingsplatz.txt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This coming year looks like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;colton@lobster:~$ tree -L 1 fy/20
fy/20
├── aiwatch
├── analysis
├── applied-analysis
├── nsf-grf
├── pandas
├── rda-image-archive
├── siparcs
└── topology-prelim
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I used my dropbox to sync notes (written in Notability on my tablet) and pdfs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;colton@lobster:~$ tree -L 1 Dropbox/
Dropbox/
├── Crypted
├── Downloads
├── export
├── import
└── todo.txt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I plan to keep pdfs in google drive and designate dropbox as my download folder. (I have an SD card for torrent files &amp;gt;2GB.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;paper&quot;&gt;Paper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am abandoning &lt;em&gt;taking notes&lt;/em&gt; on my tablet, because the generated pdfs were large (~100MB) and I realized that Notability was just another (however sleek) WYSIWYG editor in which I wasted my time and was often frustrated with formatting. The alternatives look like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;notes in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;latex&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;markdown&lt;/code&gt; on my laptop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;notes in a (chronological) series of 13x21 cm, un-ruled, &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20190516162841/https://us.moleskine.com/cahier-journal-brown/p0408&quot;&gt;cahier journals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;notes on paper, scanned as dated pdfs to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;raw&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I may scan the cahier journals pages (as done by mpacer here &lt;a href=&quot;https://mpacer.org/qualifying-exam-materials/#/qualifying-exam-written-portion/&quot;&gt;https://mpacer.org/qualifying-exam-materials/#/qualifying-exam-written-portion/&lt;/a&gt;). Primarily however, in leaving the tablet for paper, I’m following &lt;a href=&quot;https://usesthis.com/interviews/jeremy.kun/&quot;&gt;https://usesthis.com/interviews/jeremy.kun/&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… I have specificity for writing implements on par with my vim configuration. I use a very specific kind of notepad—unruled, cheap, abundant, low-weight stock—and similarly specific notebooks—small, unruled. I can never use paper or a notebook that I feel is too fancy to house my unendingly bad ideas and egregious mistakes. The only good paper is paper for which, when you throw it on the ground and grab a new sheet to start over, you don’t feel bad. Lined paper is hell. I prefer 0.9 mm lead mechanical pencils, though more often than not a 0.7 mm Bic is what I have handy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I will keep &lt;em&gt;books&lt;/em&gt; and lecture notes that are &lt;em&gt;polished and proofread&lt;/em&gt; on my tablet, to save weight and leave room in my backpack for plenty of snacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;software&quot;&gt;Software&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tersely, I subscribe to use the following software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;trello
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;for a single todo list,&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;and a single reading list.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pinboard&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;zotero&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;github&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each week, I put ~15 links in pinboard, ~30 cards in trello, and ~3 citations in zotero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I abandoned emacs org-mode for my TODO list because&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I didn’t find any use for clocking my time,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;my use was too ephemeral to properly learn org-mode’s chording,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I suffered through 2 weeks of “emacs configuration bankruptcy” in May 2018&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I couldn’t stand to edit my TODO.org file on my phone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I listen to music off my phone (connected to a Marshall Woburn Bluetooth speaker) via&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;google play music, or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the hype machine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-04-19&quot;&gt;2019-04-19&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a viscerally boring design problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;lecture notes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;laptop or notebook&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;reading scribbles&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;iPad or scratch&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;problem sets&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;laptop or iPad&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-04-08&quot;&gt;2019-04-08&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My bibliography has gotten out of control. Leo told me to stop shopping around. But how?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ask for advice?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-03-23&quot;&gt;2019-03-23&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Took a hiatus from updates to focus on coursework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trivial news: I’ve transitioned my notes and reading material to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gingerlabs.com/&quot;&gt;Notability&lt;/a&gt; for the iPad. As a result, most of my workflow is once again offline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By working from an iPad, however, I am happily meeting some immediate goals. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reading broadly for prelims,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;integrating my lecture notes with my reading notes, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;frequently grinding through exercises.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-02-01&quot;&gt;2019-02-01&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;alg2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;free modules, feedback on written work, e.g., avoid vague notation such as “Let $\phi \in \mathrm{Hom}$” [@DF04 ch. 10.3]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;diffgeo1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;manifolds with boundary, defining smooth maps, equivalent characterizations of smoothness [@Lee03, pp. 24–35]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;top2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;relative chain complexes, pairs of topological spaces, tensor product review, cohomology with coefficients in $G$ [@Bre03, section IV.5]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-31&quot;&gt;2019-01-31&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TA-ing. Not much math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-30&quot;&gt;2019-01-30&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;alg2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;subobjects, direct sums, freely generated modules [@DF04 ch. 10.3]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;diffgeo1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;smooth manifold chart lemma, Grassmannians [@Lee03, pp. 21–22]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;top2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;presentations from problem sets; handling edge cases for the first homology group&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presentations were a bit nerve-racking when I realized that I had too heavy-handedly abelianized an infinite product. (See &lt;a href=&quot;https://mathoverflow.net/questions/35397&quot;&gt;https://mathoverflow.net/questions/35397&lt;/a&gt;.) Ulrich and I found a counter example where $[\prod G_i, \prod G_i] \subsetneq \prod [G_i, G_i]$. I was then incensed to straighten out &lt;em&gt;which&lt;/em&gt; (co)products exist in &lt;em&gt;which&lt;/em&gt; concrete categories I’m usually working in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-29&quot;&gt;2019-01-29&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Revised some module theoretic arguments for Green into two-column proofs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Caught up on basic (topological) properties of manifolds.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prepared for &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/coltongrainger/fy19top2/blob/master/2019-01-30-intro-homology.pdf&quot;&gt;presentations&lt;/a&gt; in top2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was glad to attend the organizational meeting for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/view/cutopology/spring-2019?authuser=0&quot;&gt;topology seminar&lt;/a&gt;. From Beaudry’s introduction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This semester, we will cover some of the topics in homotopy theory that make an appearance in the work of Freed–Hopkins–Teleman on topological phases of matter. This seminar will be parallel to the Mathematical Physics seminar (Wednesdays from 3-4 pm in MATH 350) but will be for the most part independent. This seminar will be about topology: To understand the connections to physics, you’ll have to read on your own or go the other seminar. We have an ambitious schedule (see plan). It’s not a bad idea to read up a bit on the topics before the talks since we’ll be covering material fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://math.colorado.edu/seminars/&quot;&gt;math-physics&lt;/a&gt; seminar is co-organized with Prof &lt;a href=&quot;https://spot.colorado.edu/~hermele/&quot;&gt;Hermele&lt;/a&gt;, whose research is in theoretical condensed matter physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-28&quot;&gt;2019-01-28&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;alg2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;finitely generated modules [@DF04, ch. 10.3]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;diffgeo1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;smooth structures, transition maps [@Lee03, pp. 10–16]; spheres, level sets [@Lee03, pp. 17–23]&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;top2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;exact sequences of chain complexes, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bockstein_homomorphism&quot;&gt;Bockstein homomorphism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-27&quot;&gt;2019-01-27&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes from Clelland. Basic examples of smooth manifolds. Finished modules problem set from [@DF04, ch. 10.2].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-26&quot;&gt;2019-01-26&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes from Green on modules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-25&quot;&gt;2019-01-25&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lectures. In top2, Beaudry mentioned that “if we didn’t like that game” [forcing maps defined out of the cycle group $Z_1(X)$ to descend to the quotient $H_1(X)$] “then we would like it soon because we were about to play it &lt;em&gt;hard.&lt;/em&gt;” Lol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon, I set up definitions for functor categories and generally the category of quivers (directed graphs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked a bit with Ulrich about duality and Gelfand–Naimark, which motivated me to try and rope the content in alg2 and diffgeo1 closer together. (Ulrich also suggested that I push to do homological algebra sooner than later.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-24&quot;&gt;2019-01-24&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In prob1, we defined random variables and set up results to guarantee the existence of a random variable that’s equal in distribution to whatever probability measure we have chosen. Also defined cdfs, pdfs, and pmfs, with reference to the Lebesgue decomposition theorem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent the rest of the day TA-ing. I decided to &lt;a href=&quot;https://prooflogger.quamash.net&quot;&gt;abandon&lt;/a&gt; prooflogger since only a third of the sections had anything to do with it. I was brought to my senses by Ulrich, after he mentioned that he only attended recitations in Trondheim to drop off homework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-23&quot;&gt;2019-01-23&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lectures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In top2, we set out to prove Hurewicz’s theorem.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In alg2, we defined module homomorphisms and started to construct some sort of chain of $F[x]$-modules.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In diffgeo1, we stated topological properties of manifolds [@Lee03, pages 5–9] and exhibited spheres, products, and projective spaces as manifolds with charts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-22&quot;&gt;2019-01-22&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent the day solidifying my argument for &lt;a href=&quot;https://quamash.net/diffgeo1#banach-spaces-and-the-smooth-chain-rule&quot;&gt;the smooth chain rule in Banach spaces&lt;/a&gt;. Also finished [@DF04, section 10.1].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-21&quot;&gt;2019-01-21&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Went through Lang’s introduction [@Lan99, ch. 1] to topological vector spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-20&quot;&gt;2019-01-20&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I translated Folland’s “first look” at functional relations into intuition for the dimension and symmetric properties of repeated Fréchet derivatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I surveyed proofs for inverse function theorems and implicit function theorems [@Fol02, ch. 3.1], [@HH15, ch. 2.10], [@Lee03, no. C.34].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-19&quot;&gt;2019-01-19&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked through the motivating historical calculus in Massey’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.springer.com/us/book/9781468492330&quot;&gt;Singular Homology Theory&lt;/a&gt; [@Mas80, chapter 1]. (Massey develops homology theory with $n$-cubes rather than simplices—why? To have oriented $n$-cubes available as integrands? Does some argument/limiting process fail when working with an infinitesmally thickening mesh of simplices?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I struggled with notation for repeated applications of the Fréchet derivative. Got distracted in considering repeated linear transformations as vectors spaces themselves in the category of topological vector spaces. Skimmed related results in I.3 of Lang’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.springer.com/us/book/9780387985930&quot;&gt;Fundamentals of Differential Geometry&lt;/a&gt; [@Lan99, chapter 1].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Folland, I gladly found two problems that matched gaps in my knowledge: one to do with Lagrange multipliers and the spectral theorem, the other to do with setting up a meaningful definition of higher Fréchet derivatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Let $A$ be a symmetric $n \times n$ matrix, and let $f(\vec{x}) = (A \vec x) \cdot \vec x$ for $\vec x \in \mathbf{R}^n$. Show that the maximum and minimum of $f$ on the unit sphere ${ \vec x : \lvert\vec x\rvert = 1}$ are the largest and smallest eigenvalues of $A$. [@Fol02, number 2.9.19]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Suppose $f \colon \mathbf{R}^n \to \mathbf{R}$ is of class $C^2$; then $\nabla f$ is a $C^1$ mapping from $\mathbf{R}^n$ to itself. Show that $D(\nabla f)$ is the Hessian matrix of $f$. [@Fol02, number 2.10.6]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-18&quot;&gt;2019-01-18&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lectures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alg2: In the category of modules, we defined homomorphisms, kernels, quotients, and began to state a series of familiar isomorphism theorems [@DF04, chapter 10.2].&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diffgeo1: Stated the implicit function theorem [@Lee03, chapter C], and defined a topological manifold [@Lee03, chapter 1].&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Top2: Reasoned about long exact/non-exact sequences of abelian groups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found out that I conditionally passed the algebra prelim, and so, made a haphazard sketch of work to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;term&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;workload&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;He18&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Algebra 1, Topology 1, StatOptML (algebra prelim)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fr19&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Algebra 2, Topology 2, DiffGeo1 (topology prelim)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;So19&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;SIParCS, CU MRE, NSF apps&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;He19&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Algebra (Green, Wise, Casalaina-Martin), Analysis 1, Numerics (Bradley, Meiss, Becker, Raf)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fr20&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Analysis 2, Complex Analysis, Algebraic Topology (Pflaum, Beaudry)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;So20&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Talbot, more NSF apps, teaching&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;He20&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;topic proposal, advisors in MATH/APPM/CS&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I have 90% confidence that I will stave off probability until next year.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Update: Maybe quantum physics with Hermele next year?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-17&quot;&gt;2019-01-17&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mostly teaching, then munging surveys I had put out to the calculus sections. I went to the first meeting for a reading course in probability/measure theory. (I then had about 0.3 confidence I would drop.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reviewed the chain rule in Folland’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.math.ucla.edu/~iacoley/32H.pdf&quot;&gt;Advanced Calculus&lt;/a&gt; [@Fol99, chapter 2.3], and derivatives in several variables as linear transformations in Hubbard’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://matrixeditions.com/5thUnifiedApproach.html&quot;&gt;A Unified Approach&lt;/a&gt; [@HH15, chapter 1.7–1.9].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-16&quot;&gt;2019-01-16&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lectures again, worked to flesh out definitions for modules and simplices. Made progress in defining &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; functors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;$\Delta ( - )\colon \mathsf{Top} \to \mathsf{Ch}$ (by moving from graded abelian groups to chain complexes), and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the correspondence ‘tween $F[x]$-modules and $F$-vector spaces $V$ with a chosen endomorphism $V \to V$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-15&quot;&gt;2019-01-15&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attended offices hours for top2. Asked how to distinguish the monodromy action from action of the group of deck transformations. Got permission to stop reviewing top1 (woot!) and pass onto homology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thought about morphisms of vector spaces from a categorical perspective. Skimmed Breezer’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://linear.ups.edu/html/fcla.html&quot;&gt;FCLA&lt;/a&gt; (elementary matrices as transformations, 4 subspaces, similar and diagonal matrices). Worked through examples (especially notation) in PCM I.3.4. Slowly began to understand why one would want eigenvector bases to study subspaces “stable” under linear transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also spent an upsetting amount of time configuring pandoc on my laptop and server. Gross. I don’t even see how the software is held together. Way beyond me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-14&quot;&gt;2019-01-14&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started lecture notes for &lt;a href=&quot;https://quamash.net/top2&quot;&gt;Topology 2&lt;/a&gt; (top2), &lt;a href=&quot;https://quamash.net/diffgeo1&quot;&gt;Differential Geometry 1&lt;/a&gt; (diffgeo1), and &lt;a href=&quot;https://quamash.net/alg2&quot;&gt;Algebra 2&lt;/a&gt; (alg2). Linearity is 4sure the unifying theme of the week. Notably, diffgeo1 made a whirlwind tour of Appendix B in Lee’s &lt;em&gt;Introduction to Smooth Manifolds&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-13&quot;&gt;2019-01-13&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I previewed syllabi and reading for the next 2 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Homology in Hatcher, Bredon, and May;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Modules in Dummit &amp;amp; Foote;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Linear Algebra/Calculus review in Lee.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also setup &lt;a href=&quot;https://cu3d.github.io&quot;&gt;https://cu3d.github.io&lt;/a&gt;, a catalog of 3D-printed models, for the MARC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-12&quot;&gt;2019-01-12&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Errands. Odds &amp;amp; ends from last semester’s &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;todo.org&lt;/code&gt;. I had a lengthy, meandering conversation with two older grad students (TK &amp;amp; Carly) about faculty transitions at CU in the last 6 years. I realized how convenient &lt;a href=&quot;https://aiwatch.issarice.com&quot;&gt;https://aiwatch.issarice.com&lt;/a&gt; was for summarizing rank/career changes. Not much math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-11&quot;&gt;2019-01-11&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More teacher training. Finished my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/coltongrainger/internships/blob/master/statements/siparcs-climate-models.md&quot;&gt;SIParCS application&lt;/a&gt;. Mnemosyne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-10&quot;&gt;2019-01-10&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attended teacher training. Finished transcribing an &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/coltongrainger/neural-network/blob/master/posts/2018-09-10-leah-buechley.md&quot;&gt;interview with Leah Buechley&lt;/a&gt;. Setup duplicity with google cloud platform. Defragmented my gmail archive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-09&quot;&gt;2019-01-09&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Took the topology prelim. Answered 3 of 6 questions in point-set and algebraic topology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;separation properties&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;applications of Seifert van-Kampen&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;homotopy groups of real projective space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked to TK: what to review for differential geometry?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;multilinear forms up to the definition of a tensor product&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;implicit and inverse function theorems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-08&quot;&gt;2019-01-08&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More chores, etc. I installed KeePassX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-07&quot;&gt;2019-01-07&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a chore and measure of progress, I attempted the algebra prelim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I struggled to understand possible group actions of $Q_8$ on ${1, \ldots, n}$. In a dilemma, I wrote out a treacherously long table of conjugacy classes for $S_n$, $n = 4, \ldots, 7$ and made a confusing argument about normal subgroups as unions of conjugacy classes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Afterwards, Andre and I discovered a one-liner to show “$Q_8 \le S_n$” is absurd for these cases.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;When $Q_8$ acts on $I_n$ for $n &amp;lt; 8$, the stabilizer of any point in $I_n$ contains $-1$, whence $-1$ is in the kernel of the action.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also afterwards, when I needed to determine which primes in $\mathbf{Z}$ were also Gaussian primes, I found myself impressed with Weissstein’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MathWorld&quot;&gt;MathWorld&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I expect the Slack channel Chris and I were using to study will soon be defunct.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To shift gears for topology, I passed over a survey: &lt;a href=&quot;http://catdir.loc.gov/catdir/toc/ecip0818/2008020450.html&quot;&gt;PCM IV.10&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-06&quot;&gt;2019-01-06&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris and I ran through Micky’s group theory notes. I discovered Zassenhaus’ &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=_lOycgz7bQYC&quot;&gt;The Theory of Groups&lt;/a&gt; and skimmed through chapter IV on $p$-groups and Sylow $p$-groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To de-stress before the prelim, I browsed the OED for historical uses of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;morphism&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;quaternion&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;group&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ring&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;field&lt;/code&gt;. (I found Zassenhaus under &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;quaternions&lt;/code&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-05&quot;&gt;2019-01-05&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continued to atomicize mnemosyne cards by expanding “naive” procedural topics from the GRE. I went through a proof of Sylow’s theorems and thought about the conjugation and left translation action of a group $G$ on its $p$-groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--
I set up a [fact sheet for internship applications](https://github.com/coltongrainger/internships) this summer.
--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-04&quot;&gt;2019-01-04&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris and I sat for a timed &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/coltongrainger/fy19alg1/blob/master/2019-01-04-algebra-sep-practice.md&quot;&gt;practice exam&lt;/a&gt;, adapted from Ed Dummit’s 2014 &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/a/wisc.edu/math-intranet/home/quals&quot;&gt;algebra summer enhancement program&lt;/a&gt;. I feel silly taking the exam before I know what I’m doing, but&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there’s a timeline, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our dept chair emphasizes &lt;a href=&quot;http://math.colorado.edu/~kstange/gradstudy.pdf&quot;&gt;“trusting oneself”&lt;/a&gt; to seek out “new challenges and novel contexts”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her accompanying advice is, of course, to “doubt oneself” and “build what you know”, which I look forward to reverting to after next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I compiled Micky Steinberg’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.wisc.edu/~micky/grouptheory.pdf&quot;&gt;2014 group theory notes&lt;/a&gt; into a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/coltongrainger/fy19alg1/blob/master/2019-01-05-algebra-micky-practice.md&quot;&gt;light-hearted practice exam&lt;/a&gt; for tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-03&quot;&gt;2019-01-03&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris talked me through problems 1–3 on CU’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/coltongrainger/prelims/blob/master/2008-01-15-cu-algebra-prelim.pdf&quot;&gt;Jan 2008 algebra prelim&lt;/a&gt;, which I didn’t understand. For prob 2, we needed to make a recursive argument to find a nontrivial abelian normal subgroup of prime power order in a finite solvable group. Ian also mentioned this problem (with enthusiasm) before break, so I might revisit it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started reviewing from &lt;a href=&quot;http://matrixeditions.com/5thUnifiedApproach.html&quot;&gt;Hubbard&lt;/a&gt;, following the &lt;a href=&quot;https://canvas.harvard.edu/courses/45219/pages/weekly-schedule&quot;&gt;week 1&lt;/a&gt; schedule for Paul Bamberg’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://canvas.harvard.edu/courses/45219/files/6701269/download?verifier=Yvcu1AARsTzhWbCTmjtM2cT0BWA4sCCxBS3VftOE&amp;amp;wrap=1&quot;&gt;Math 23a&lt;/a&gt;. (The supplemental materials for math 23a are great, and I think I’ll exhaust most of my free time before Jan 14 going over these.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I went through exercises in I.1 Fields from Halmos’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.springer.com/us/book/9780387900933&quot;&gt;Finite Dimensional Vector Spaces&lt;/a&gt;, which is admittedly out of date. I’m going through Halmos, however, because&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I found a hardcopy in the math dept’s reading room, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I was impressed when I skimmed &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=16829440&quot;&gt;Halmos’s and Steenrod’s&lt;/a&gt; 1973 &lt;em&gt;How to Write Mathematics&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-02&quot;&gt;2019-01-02&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Distracted today: I setup yst to compile yaml data into a &lt;a href=&quot;https://coltongrainger.com/cv&quot;&gt;CV&lt;/a&gt;, as per Dom Moritz’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://domoritz.de/cv/&quot;&gt;https://domoritz.de/cv/&lt;/a&gt;. Dom’s job-hunting stress thoroughly dosed me (by proxy) with timeline stress, and, incidentally, I spent the day “signalling”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-01-01&quot;&gt;2019-01-01&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I revised cards on introductory measure theory, also group actions. I continued through a backlog of reviews I owed mnemosyne from last semester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Oddly as well, I flicked through photos from 2018 back to the beginning of 2016, when I was skiing a bit and preparing to graduate. From my undergraduate coursework, maybe I’m only interested to mnemo-fy notes from electricity and magnetism? from ordinary differential equations?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2019-12-31&quot;&gt;2019-12-31&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent some time convincing myself that “chunking mathematical concepts” would be more rewarding “completing prerequisites in a satisfactory order” after reading Michael Nielsen’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://augmentingcognition.com/ltm.html&quot;&gt;essay on anki&lt;/a&gt;. I reactivated &lt;a href=&quot;https://quamash.net/maths-GRE&quot;&gt;mnemosyne cards&lt;/a&gt; I had made studying for the math GRE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While revising cards I had starred for typos, I began to recognize I’d been trying to chunk concepts that were too complex for a first pass. (I found a particularly bad batch of measure theory cards—should delete these or just atomicize them?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!---
I finally setup a bitcoin wallet and skimmed [bitcoin is worse is better](https://www.gwern.net/Bitcoin-is-Worse-is-Better).
---&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2018-12-30&quot;&gt;2018-12-30&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished &lt;a href=&quot;https://prooflogger.quamash.net&quot;&gt;https://prooflogger.quamash.net&lt;/a&gt;, which I hope Lee will allow me to force some of the calculus sections to use. &lt;a href=&quot;https://quamash.net/math1300#participation&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is an outline I’d give students. I aim to game students into presenting proofs to each other and providing constructive oral feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2018-12-29&quot;&gt;2018-12-29&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought about social support networks while travelling from Idaho back to Boulder, e.g., &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pgbovine.net/PG-Vlog-252-cohort-effects.htm&quot;&gt;the cohort effect&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2018-12-27&quot;&gt;2018-12-27&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following &lt;a href=&quot;https://nadiaeghbal.com/notes&quot;&gt;https://nadiaeghbal.com/notes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://issarice.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;https://issarice.wordpress.com/&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/M2pGiBrw-Ns?t=422&quot;&gt;https://youtu.be/M2pGiBrw-Ns?t=422&lt;/a&gt; I’m starting a working journal with a broad scope: early graduate school in the mathematics department at CU Boulder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This journal supersedes my now obsolete &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.coltongrainger.com&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t gotten permission to emulate any one of the above authors, so I’m sort of planning to write in a manner that oscillates between each’s style. In spite of the common medium (~daily entries) it seems each author’s motivation is tangential to the other two’s: writing for exploration, for transparency, for reflection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine I will be keeping this journal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to narrate what I’ve been working on in a chronological fashion,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to give myself encouragement by tracking progress through my coursework,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to urge myself on (as in ski-racing, where we’d often yell at each other “up up up!”).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it would be appropriate to include characteristic quotes, which motivate this journal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nadia Eghbal (&lt;a href=&quot;https://nadiaeghbal.com/notes/&quot;&gt;notes&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;11/26/18&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Realizing that I love to be alone, like in a physically low-stimulation environment, but I still think of myself as socially oriented even in that context. I still like texting/FaceTiming friends. And: I only want to be alone to work on ideas that I eventually take back to others. Like, if I were just writing for the sake of writing and not publishing it out, I’d probably get pretty bored and antsy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;11/26/18&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Amplification vs. exploration: Usually I say that I prefer writing to talks/interviews bc I can think better through writing over speaking. But I think another big reason is bc people often want you to talk about stuff you’ve already done, which is not that interesting to me. Whereas with blog posts, it’s my blog, I don’t really care if you read it or not, I’m just putting stuff out there and hopefully connecting with a few ppl who feel the same way. To me, writing is pushing to the edges, exploring the limits of my identity and what I’m comfortable sharing in public. Whereas any other form of communicating ideas feels performative: I’m rehashing things I already know, and that you know me for. Also why I had to get off Medium (bc it made blogging feel performative)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Issa Rice (&lt;a href=&quot;https://issarice.wordpress.com/2018/12/01/a-note-on-scope-of-updates/&quot;&gt;a note on scope of updates&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As I stated at the beginning, this blog came about because I wanted to make available information about “what I’m up to” in cases where “what I’m up to” doesn’t naturally lead to public updates. So I think it’s not so important to record things on here when the same information can be obtained through other sources (i.e. my public activity on other websites).&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;However, I also want to have some kind of conceptual coherence about this blog. And since the overlap between “my activity that doesn’t naturally lead to public updates but where I would like to make public updates available” and “my AI safety learning” is nearly perfect, I think I will track the former by writing about the latter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philip Guo (&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/M2pGiBrw-Ns?t=272&quot;&gt;vlog transcript, talking about his journal&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;anyways so when I started my postdoc I thought of this idea I don’t know how I thought of it but I thought this idea that I would just keep a running diary of anything that I’ve encountered that to work-related that I felt like writing down. so it was very simple. I created a text file. this is my first one (reading it) this is really funny I’m just reading this. this is July 2013, my first month as a postdoc.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;July 2013 I’m going to start a rough weekly work diary reflecting on my thoughts about life as a young academic. I need to focus more on how I feel rather than what I did since it’s easy to later reconstruct what I did from other artifacts but it’s hard to recreate old feelings. this diary is gonna be quite rough and I don’t want to hold myself to a strict writing schedule. let’s keep this fairly freeform and low-key.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;once again in parentheses I said: focus on how I feel rather than just what I did&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Colton Grainger</name></author><summary type="html">Summary</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Software Engineering?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/software-engineering-personal-statement" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Software Engineering?" /><published>2020-05-12T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-05-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/software-engineering-personal-statement</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/software-engineering-personal-statement">&lt;p&gt;Because I want to contribute to a community of creative individuals in my hometown, Boise, I intend to pivot in my career trajectory to take an engineering position &lt;em&gt;developing software and manipulating exotic datasets&lt;/em&gt;, rather than returning to graduate school at CU Boulder this Fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My immediate qualifications include&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a year of professional &lt;strong&gt;software engineering&lt;/strong&gt; experience at the National Center for Atmospheric Research and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;background in &lt;strong&gt;mathematics and data science&lt;/strong&gt; that drives me to produce high-quality software.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;While I am well-equipped to work independently, I am new to software engineering as a collaborative process.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, at NCAR, I worked &lt;em&gt;independently&lt;/em&gt; under two project scientists on the reduction of meteorological data from binary image files using Python and SQLAlchemy. Starting from scratch, I designed a metadata schema and ingest system for a ~60 TB collection of scanned documents to reduce each ~6 MB image to about ~2 KB of (meteorological time-series) metadata, and I developed this workflow to completion over a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For collaboration and project management, I’ve used &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;org-mode&lt;/code&gt;, git issues, and kan-ban style boards. Though I have only a few months’ experience working with teams to plan and prioritize a backlog, I am &lt;em&gt;endearingly hopeful&lt;/em&gt; to have more soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Doing mathematics, I learned how to have problem-solving conversations with myself and others; doing data science, I learned additionally how to describe and implement a solution in its domain-specific language.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I am confident that I could (i) quickly assimilate technical domain knowledge; (ii) proactively investigate and solve issues arising from questions posed by clients; and (iii) design well-documented data processing workflows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To be explicit&lt;/strong&gt;. A subset of the technical tools I am confident using looks like: 
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;apache&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bash&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;debian&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Excel&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gcloud&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pickle&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;MongoDB&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;MySQL&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;nginx&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pandas&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PostgreSQL&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;python3&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;scipy&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;statistics&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SQLAlchemy&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;unittest&lt;/code&gt;. 
I would need to “book up”, but I could also quickly be proficient with Amazon Web Services, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Java&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;C&lt;/code&gt; dialects.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Colton Grainger</name></author><summary type="html">Because I want to contribute to a community of creative individuals in my hometown, Boise, I intend to pivot in my career trajectory to take an engineering position developing software and manipulating exotic datasets, rather than returning to graduate school at CU Boulder this Fall.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What’s on my Kindle?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ereader-library" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What's on my Kindle?" /><published>2019-09-07T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-09-07T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ereader-library</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ereader-library">&lt;p&gt;Today, I biked to Longmont, got stood up by a craigslist seller, and decided to buy a Kindle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the roster of pdf files that I’m going to keep on the Kindle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1965-milnor-topology-from-the-differentiable-viewpoint.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1974-guillemin-pollack-Differential-Topology.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1974-hirsch-smale-differential-equations-dynamical-systems-and-linear-algebra.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1974-milnor-stasheff-characteristic-classes.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1982-bott-tu-differential-forms-in-algebraic-topology.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1983-warner-foundations-of-differentiable-manifolds-and-lie-groups.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1986-rudin-real-and-complex-analysis.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1990-lang-undergraduate-algebra.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1991-artin-algebra.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1993-bredon-topology-and-geometry.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1994-baez-muniain-gauge-theories-knots-and-gravity.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1994-spivak-calculus.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1995-hubbard-linear-algebra-appendix-DifferentialEquationsADynamicalApproach.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1995-rotman-intro-to-theory-of-groups.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1996-robinson-a-course-in-the-theory-of-groups.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1999-folland-real-analysis.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1999-lang-FundamentalsOfDifferentialGeom.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1999-may-a_concise_course_in_algebraic_topology.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2002-aguilar-gitler-prieto-algebraic-topology-from-a-homotopical-viewpoint-springer.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2002-ash-abstract_algebra.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2002-folland-advanced-calculus.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2002-lang-algebra.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2002-lang-IntroductionToDifferentialMani.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2003-lawson-topology-a-geometric-approach.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2003-lee-introduction_to_smooth_manifolds.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2005-beardon-algebra-and-geometry.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2005-boas-mathematical-methods-in-the-physicals-sciences.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2006-chicone-ordinary-differential-equations-with-applications.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2007-korner-part-1a-analysis.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2008-brase-and-brase-understandable-statistics.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2008-isaacs-finite-group-theory.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2008-viro-ivanov-netzvetaev-kharlamov-elementary-topology-problem-textbook.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2009-aluffi-algebra-chapter-0.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2009-folland-guide-to-advanced-real-analysis.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2009-jeffery-lee-manifolds-and-differential-geometry.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2009-tao-245a-measure-book.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2009-treil-linear-algebra-done-wrong.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2010-royden-fitzpatrick-real-analysis.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2011-lee-intro-to-topological-manifolds.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2012-frankel-the-geometry-of-physics.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2014-riehl-category-theory-in-context.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2014-tanaka-math-230a-omnibus.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2015-axler-linear-algebra-done-right.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2015-riehl-on-the-construction-of-new-topological-spaces.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2016-AMU-probability-and-statistics-with-R.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2016-leinster-basic-category-theory.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2016-naik-linear-algebra-lecture-omnibus.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2016-zorich-mathematical-analysis-II.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2017-meiss-differential-dynamical-systems.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2017-sjamaar-manifolds-and-differential-forms.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2018-herrlich-algebra_1.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2018-lee-introduction-to-riemannian-manifolds.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2019-openintro-statistics.pdf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Roger Peng published some native Kindle format books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;artofdatascience.mobi&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rprogramming.mobi&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Colton Grainger</name></author><summary type="html">Today, I biked to Longmont, got stood up by a craigslist seller, and decided to buy a Kindle.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Status and Overhead</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/status-and-overhead" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Status and Overhead" /><published>2018-12-31T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-12-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/status-and-overhead</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/status-and-overhead">&lt;p&gt;Since August, I have been overly concerned with status and overhead. I’m taken up with status, I think, because it’s new to me. Prior to Boulder, I was in Olympia, and I didn’t interact with anyone (in person, at least) who actually &lt;em&gt;put me into rank&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m newly stressed out by “overhead”: both in the sense of labor-time and in the sense of being plainly confused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Perhaps I should have taken more rigorous prerequisite courses? Or exerted myself more diligently over the summer prior to graduate school?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a skeleton argument to dismiss both concerns as frivolous and distracting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Status&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It’s just culture shock. Olympia is a backwoods compared to Boulder, and certainly Boulder is a backwoods compared to larger metropolitan areas.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It encourages me to over-commit. For example, I botched the neural network podcast. But why did I feel like I should I have gotten involved in the first place?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It’s timocratical. Just a love of honor. What sort of motivation is that?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It’s foolish. For example, I broke my hand while biking without enough sleep.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Overhead&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It’s inevitable: I  will always have less technical knowledge than is good for me.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It’s easily dealt with by being modest.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It’s required. For example, TA-ing is a condition of my studies.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of the 5 days before finals I felt decent: I could work all day, I was competing directly with myself, and I wasn’t responsible for new material. I also settled into a paper-based workflow. I carried around a few notebooks with as many practice exams as I needed, and I stopped updating quamash.net.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Colton Grainger</name></author><summary type="html">Since August, I have been overly concerned with status and overhead. I’m taken up with status, I think, because it’s new to me. Prior to Boulder, I was in Olympia, and I didn’t interact with anyone (in person, at least) who actually put me into rank.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bang Expressions on DuckDuckGo</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/duckduckgo" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bang Expressions on DuckDuckGo" /><published>2018-08-12T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-08-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/duckduckgo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/duckduckgo">&lt;p&gt;Appealing to the collective wisdom of non-google searchers, here’s a curated table of bang expressions available on duckduckgo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ACL Anthology ` !acl ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aclweb.org/portal/what-is-cl&quot;&gt;“What is the ACL and what is Computational Linguistics? ACL Member Portal”&lt;/a&gt;. “The Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL) is the premier international scientific and professional society for people working on computational problems involving human language, a field often referred to as either computational linguistics or natural language processing (NLP). The association was founded in 1962, originally named the Association for Machine Translation and Computational Linguistics (AMTCL), and became the ACL in 1968. Activities of the ACL include the holding of an annual meeting each summer and the sponsoring of the journal Computational Linguistics, published by MIT Press; this conference and journal are the leading publications of the field. For more information, see: https://www.aclweb.org/.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ACM Guide ` !acm ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://libraries.acm.org/digital-library/acm-guide-to-computing-literature&quot;&gt;“The ACM Guide to Computing Literature”&lt;/a&gt;. “The ACM Guide to Computing Literature is the most comprehensive bibliographic database in existence today focused exclusively on the field of computing, making this A&amp;amp;I service—which seamlessly integrates with ACM’s full-text articles—a true starting point for anyone looking to search and access computing’s rapidly growing archive. More than an index, the Guide to Computing Literature serves as the engine that drives the most exciting functionality of the ACM Digital Library, including features such as ACM Author Profile Pages, which includes bibliographic and bibliometric data for over 1,500,000 authors in the field of computer science, and the ACM Institutional Profile Pages, which includes bibliographic and bibliometric data for every academic, government, and industry organization publishing articles in the field.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AMS MathScinet ` !msc ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MathSciNet&quot;&gt;“MathSciNet - Wikipedia”&lt;/a&gt;. English Wikipedia. “MathSciNet is a searchable online bibliographic database created by the American Mathematical Society in 1996. It contains all of the contents of the journal Mathematical Reviews (MR) since 1940 along with an extensive author database, links to other MR entries, citations, full journal entries, and links to original articles. It contains almost 3 million items and over 1.7 million links to original articles. Along with its parent publication Mathematical Reviews, MathSciNet has become an essential tool for researchers in the mathematical sciences. Access to the database is by subscription only and is not generally available to individual researchers who are not affiliated with a larger subscribing institution.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Art of Problem Solving [Wiki] ` !aops ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Rusczyk#The_Art_of_Problem_Solving&quot;&gt;“Richard Rusczyk - Wikipedia”&lt;/a&gt;. English Wikipedia. “In 1994, Rusczyk and Sandor Lehoczky wrote the Art of Problem Solving books, designed to prepare students for mathematical competitions by teaching them concepts and problem solving methods rarely taught in school. These books lent their name to the company he founded in 2003.After working for four years as a bond trader for D. E. Shaw &amp;amp; Co., Rusczyk created the Art of Problem Solving web site, which provides resources for middle and high school students to develop their mathematics and problem solving abilities. These include real-time competitions to solve math problems and on-line tools to learn how to solve problems with increasing difficulty as well as math forums. Rusczyk has also published the Art of Problem Solving series of books aimed at a similar audience. The site also provides fee-based online mathematics classes, which range from Prealgebra to Group Theory and Calculus.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Computer Science (Stack Exchange) ` !csse ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://cs.stackexchange.com/help/on-topic&quot;&gt;“What topics can I ask about here?”&lt;/a&gt;. Computer Science Stack Exchange. “Computer Science Stack Exchange is for students, researchers and practitioners of computer science.Computer science, also sometimes called computing science, is the science of computation and its applications. This site covers theoretical and applied computer science at any level, including but not limited to: algorithms, models of computation;    programming language semantics, formal methods;    computer architecture, networks;    machine learning, artificial intelligence, knowledge representation, natural language processing;    vision, graphics.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cross Validated (Stack Exchange) ` !crossvalidated ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.stackexchange.com/help/on-topic&quot;&gt;“What topics can I ask about here?”&lt;/a&gt;. Cross Validated. “CrossValidated is for statisticians, data miners, and anyone else doing data analysis or interested in it as a discipline. If you have a question about statistical analysis, applied or theoretical; designing experiments; collecting data; data mining; machine learning;    visualizing data;    probability theory;    mathematical statistics;    statistical and data-driven computing; then you’re in the right place.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Göttinger Digitalsieriungszentrum ` !gdz ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Center_for_Retrospective_Digitization&quot;&gt;“Center for Retrospective Digitization - Wikipedia”&lt;/a&gt;. English Wikipedia. “The Center for Retrospective Digitization in Göttingen (German: Göttinger DigitalisierungsZentrum, GDZ) is an online system for archiving academic journals maintained by the University of Göttingen.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hgpu.org ` !hgpu ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://hgpu.org/?page_id=2&quot;&gt;“About”&lt;/a&gt;. hgpu.org. June 5, 2018. “hgpu.org is a resource for people who seek the possibility to accelerate their computations by means of Graphics Processing Units (GPU). The site contains links to reviews, tutorials, research papers, program packages concerning various aspects of graphics and non-graphics (general purpose computing) using of GPU and related parallel architectures (FPGA, Cell processors etc.). The site also collects and cataloged information about programming tools and modern hardware for development of GPU applications.” See the &lt;a href=&quot;https://hgpu.org/?page_id=1109&quot;&gt;tags&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IACR ` !iacr ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iacr.org/&quot;&gt;“International Association for Cryptologic Research”&lt;/a&gt;. “The International Association for Cryptologic Research (IACR) is a non-profit scientific organization whose purpose is to further research in cryptology and related fields. Cryptology is the science and practice of designing computation and communication systems which are secure in the presence of adversaries.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Images des mathématiques ` !imaths ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Images_des_math%C3%A9matiques&quot;&gt;“Images des mathématiques — Wikipédia”&lt;/a&gt;. Wikipedia. “Images des mathématiques (ou Images des maths) est un site web français édité par le CNRS et consacré à la vulgarisation en mathématiques. Il a pour but de montrer la diversité des mathématiques sous un aspect attractif. Il est sous-titré la recherche mathématique en mots et en images.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inverse Symbolic Calculator ` !isc ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://isc.carma.newcastle.edu.au/advanced&quot;&gt;“Inverse Symbolic Calculator Plus”&lt;/a&gt;. “The Inverse Symbolic Calculator (ISC) uses a combination of lookup tables and integer relation algorithms in order to associate a closed form representation with a user-defined, truncated decimal expansion (written as a floating point expression). The lookup tables include a substantial data set compiled by S. Plouffe both before and during his period as an employee at CECM.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IXL ` !ixl ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IXL_Learning&quot;&gt;“IXL Learning - Wikipedia”&lt;/a&gt;. English Wikipedia. “IXL Learning is an American educational technology company based in San Mateo, California. The company’s main product is IXL.com, a website primarily offering educational practice for K-12 students.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Library Genesis ` !genlib ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Library_Genesis&quot;&gt;“Library Genesis - Wikipedia”&lt;/a&gt;. English Wikipedia. “Library Genesis or LibGen is a search engine for articles and books on various topics, which allows free access to content that is otherwise paywalled or not digitized elsewhere. Among others, it carries PDFs of content from Elsevier’s ScienceDirect web-portal.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mathematical Association of America ` !maa ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.maa.org/about-maa/maa-history&quot;&gt;“MAA History Mathematical Association of America”&lt;/a&gt;. “The MAA was established in 1915. But the roots of the Association can be traced to the 1894 founding of the American Mathematical Monthly by Benjamin Finkel, who wrote “Most of our existing journals deal almost exclusively with subjects beyond the reach of the average student or teacher of mathematics or at least with subjects with which they are familiar, and little, if any, space, is devoted to the solution of problems…No pains will be spared on the part of the Editors to make this the most interesting and most popular journal published in America.”” Searches the MAA meetings, press/news, curriculum, and competitions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mathematics (Stack Exchange) ` !mathse ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://math.stackexchange.com/help/on-topic&quot;&gt;“What topics can I ask about here? - Help Center”&lt;/a&gt;. Mathematics Stack Exchange. “Mathematics Stack Exchange is for people studying mathematics at any level and professionals in related fields. We welcome questions about:    Understanding mathematical concepts and theorems.    Mathematical problems such as one might come across in a course or textbook. (First read our how to ask a good question page.)    Solving mathematical puzzles.    Software that mathematicians use (except Mathematica, which has its own Stack Exchange site).”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MathOverflow ` !mathoverflow or !mo ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MathOverflow&quot;&gt;“MathOverflow - Wikipedia”&lt;/a&gt;. English Wikipedia. “MathOverflow is a mathematics website, which serves both as a collaborative blog and an online community of mathematicians. It allows users to ask questions, submit answers, and rate both, all while getting merit points for their activities. It is a part of the Stack Exchange Network.It is primarily for asking questions on mathematics research – i.e. related to unsolved problems and the extension of knowledge of mathematics into areas that are not yet known – and does not welcome requests from non-mathematicians for instruction, for example homework exercises. It does welcome various questions on other topics that might normally be discussed among mathematicians, for example about publishing, refereeing, advising, getting tenure, etc. It is generally inhospitable to questions perceived as tendentious or argumentative. ”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matlab File Exchange `  !matlabfx ` Now-a-days one should try &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mikecroucher/awesome-MATLAB&quot;&gt;awesome-MATLAB&lt;/a&gt;: “A curated list of awesome MATLAB toolboxes, applications, software and resources.” Mostly under BSD licensces.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NIST Digital Library of Mathematical Functions ` !dlmf ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nist.gov/publications/nist-digital-library-mathematical-functions&quot;&gt;“DLMF”&lt;/a&gt;. NIST. May 1, 2003. “NIST (formerly, National Bureau of Standards) has started an ambitious project that aims to produce a successor to Abramowitz and Stegun’s Handbook of Mathematical Functions, published by the National Bureau of Standards in 1964 and reprinted by Dover in 1965. Both editions continue to sell briskly and are widely cited inthe scientific literature. However, with the many advances in the theory, computation and application of special functions that have occurred since 1960, a new standard reference is badly needed. NIST intends to satisfy this need by providing a Digital Library of Mathematical Functions (DLMF) as a free Web site together with an associated book and CD-ROM.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;nLab ` !nl or !ncatlab ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NLab&quot;&gt;“nLab - Wikipedia”&lt;/a&gt;. English Wikipedia. “The nLab is a wiki for research-level notes, expositions and collaborative work, including original research, in mathematics, physics, and philosophy, with a focus on methods from category theory and homotopy theory. The nLab espouses the “n-point of view” (a deliberate pun on Wikipedia’s “neutral point of view”) that category theory and particularly higher n-category theory provide a useful unifying viewpoint for mathematics, physics and philosophy. The nLab is listed on MathOverflow as a standard online mathematics reference to check before asking questions. Many questions and answers link to the nLab for background material. It is one of two wikis mentioned by the mathematical physicist John C. Baez in his review of math blogs for the American Mathematical Society.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Physics Forums `  !physics ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.physicsforums.com/help/aboutus/&quot;&gt;“About Physics Forums”&lt;/a&gt;. “Our goal is to provide a community for people (whether students, professional scientists, or hobbyists) to learn and discuss science as it is currently generally understood and practiced by the professional scientific community. As our name suggests, our main focus is on physics, but we also have forums for most other academic areas including engineering, chemistry, biology, social sciences, etc. Physics help along with math help and other sciences is available for students.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PlanetMath ` !planetmath ` &lt;a href=&quot;http://planetmath.org/&quot;&gt;“PlanetMath.org”&lt;/a&gt;. “PlanetMath is a virtual community which aims to help make mathematical knowledge more accessible. PlanetMath’s content is created collaboratively: the main feature is the mathematics encyclopedia with entries written and reviewed by members. The entries are contributed under the terms of the Creative Commons By/Share-Alike License in order to preserve the rights of authors, readers and other content creators in a sensible way. Entries are written in LaTeX, the lingua franca of the worldwide mathematical community. Articles are then rendered for presentation on the web using LaTeXML, and links between them are added using NNexus. As of 2018, source files are editable via planetmath’s repositories on Github: acceptable pull requests will be merged by one of our Editors. The PlanetMath.org website is hosted by the University of Waterloo Faculty of Mathematics. PlanetMath.org, Ltd., is a 501(c)3 nonprofit, incorporated in Alexandria, Virginia, USA.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Proof Wiki ` !proof ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://proofwiki.org/wiki/ProofWiki:About&quot;&gt;“ProofWiki:About”&lt;/a&gt;. “ProofWiki is dedicated to providing a place where people can take their knowledge of math proofs and share it online. Anyone can add or edit articles on math proofs from any field of mathematics. ProofWiki was started in April 2008, and is maintained by Joe with the help of Alec Cooper, prime.mover and Lord_Farin.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SageMath Documentation ` !sage ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sagemath.org/library.html&quot;&gt;“SageMath Mathematical Software System”&lt;/a&gt;. “The SageMath Standard Documentation includes the whole SageMath documentation in HTML and PDF formats: installation, construction of statements, reference manual, etc.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Complexity Zoo ` !cz `  &lt;a href=&quot;https://complexityzoo.uwaterloo.ca/Zoo_Intro&quot;&gt;“Complexity Zoo Introduction - Complexity Zoo”&lt;/a&gt;. “The sprawling web of known relations among complexity classes - containments, oracle separations, random oracle separations, lowness results, the occasional inequality - is not fixed in my memory like the English language. And so it’s largely for my own benefit that I recorded a chunk of what’s known in one unwieldy HTML file.The second audience is other theorists and theory students, who might find the Zoo to have a few advantages as a reference. First, inspired by Eric Weisstein’s famed World of Mathematics, it links liberally between entries. Second, it can be updated regularly - much of its current content is not yet in any book as far as I know. Third, it takes a democratic approach to complexity classes, with big hitters like NP listed alongside the lesser-known mAL, PODN, and QACC0. Any class is fair game so long as something nontrivial has been said about it in the literature.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Online Encyclopedia Of Integer Sequences ` !seq ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On-Line_Encyclopedia_of_Integer_Sequences&quot;&gt;“On-Line Encyclopedia of Integer Sequences - Wikipedia”&lt;/a&gt;. English Wikipedia. “The On-Line Encyclopedia of Integer Sequences (OEIS), also cited simply as Sloane’s, is an online database of integer sequences. It was created and maintained by Neil Sloane while a researcher at AT&amp;amp;T Labs.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wolfram Mathematica Reference ` !wlr ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wolfram_Mathematica&quot;&gt;“Wolfram Mathematica - Wikipedia”&lt;/a&gt;. English Wikipedia. “Wolfram Mathematica (usually termed Mathematica) is a modern technical computing system spanning most areas of technical computing — including neural networks, machine learning, image processing, geometry, data science, visualizations, and others. The system is used in many technical, scientific, engineering, mathematical, and computing fields. It was conceived by Stephen Wolfram and is developed by Wolfram Research of Champaign, Illinois.The Wolfram Language is the programming language used in Mathematica.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wolfram MathWorld ` !mathworld ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MathWorld&quot;&gt;“MathWorld - Wikipedia”&lt;/a&gt;. English Wikipedia. “MathWorld is an online mathematics reference work, created and largely written by Eric W. Weisstein. It is sponsored by and licensed to Wolfram Research, Inc. and was partially funded by the National Science Foundation’s National Science Digital Library grant to the University of Illinois at Urbana–Champaign. ”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zentralblatt MATH Database ` !zbmath ` &lt;a href=&quot;https://zbmath.org/about/&quot;&gt;“zbMATH”&lt;/a&gt;. “Zentralblatt MATH (zbMATH) is the world’s most comprehensive and longest-running abstracting and reviewing service in pure and applied mathematics. It is edited by the European Mathematical Society (EMS), the Heidelberg Academy of Sciences and Humanities and FIZ Karlsruhe. zbMATH provides easy access to bibliographic data, reviews and abstracts from all areas of pure mathematics as well as applications, in particular to natural sciences, computer science, economics and engineering. It also covers history and philosophy of mathematics and university education. All entries are classified according to the Mathematics Subject Classification Scheme (MSC 2010) and are equipped with keywords in order to characterize their particular content.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Colton Grainger</name></author><summary type="html">Appealing to the collective wisdom of non-google searchers, here’s a curated table of bang expressions available on duckduckgo.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Navigating Courses at CU Boulder</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/navigating-with-kate" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Navigating Courses at CU Boulder" /><published>2018-08-06T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-08-06T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/navigating-with-kate</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/navigating-with-kate">&lt;p&gt;A survey of curriculum for first year PhD students in the maths department at CU Boulder, looking at cousin disciplines (applied maths, physics, computer science) and other universities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;collaboration-with-applied-maths-cs-and-physics&quot;&gt;Collaboration with applied maths, CS, and physics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see two ways of getting involved. I could attend talks (this is easy) and/or take courses (this would be hard, as I’d have to petition and the courses are outside my focus).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided not to take any outside courses, but will certainly attend the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/colorado.edu/statoptml/&quot;&gt;StatOptML&lt;/a&gt; seminar and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.colorado.edu/physics/events/seminars-and-colloquia&quot;&gt;physics colloquium&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;external-courses-and-seminars&quot;&gt;External courses and seminars&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;APPM&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.colorado.edu/group/applied_mathematics&quot;&gt;Applied Maths Seminar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.colorado.edu/amath/sites/default/files/attached-files/supplement_16-17.pdf&quot;&gt;APPM sequence courses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;thead&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;APPM&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;Fall&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;Spring&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;/thead&gt;
      &lt;tbody&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5380-5390&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Modeling in Applied Maths&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Modeling in Maths-Bio&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5430-5470&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Complex Variables&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;PDEs and Integral Equations&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5440-5450&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Applied Analysis 1&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Applied Analysis 2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5460-5470&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Dynamical Systems&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;PDEs and Integral Equations&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5470-5480&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;PDEs and Integral Equations&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Approximation Methods&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5520-5540&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Intro to Stats&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Intro to Time Series&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5520-5560&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Intro to Stats&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Markov Processes&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5600-5610&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Numerical Analysis 1&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Numerical Analysis 2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5590-5380&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Statistical Modeling&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Modeling in Applied Maths&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5590-5520&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Statistical Modeling&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Intro to Stats&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5590-5540&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Statistical Modeling&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Intro to Time Series&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5590-5560&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Statistical Modeling&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Markov Processes&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5590-5580&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Statistical Modeling&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Statistical Software&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;/tbody&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;CSCI&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.colorado.edu/cs-theory/theory-seminar&quot;&gt;Theory Seminar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bouldertheory&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@bouldertheory&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.colorado.edu/cs-theory/&quot;&gt;CS core courses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;thead&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;CSCI&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;course&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;/thead&gt;
      &lt;tbody&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5454&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Algorithms&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5444&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Theory of Computation&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5654&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Linear and Integer Programming&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;6564&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Advanced Algorithms&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5254&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Convex Optimization&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;7000&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Cryptography and Cryptanalysis&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;/tbody&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;PHYS&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.colorado.edu/physics/events/seminars-and-colloquia&quot;&gt;Physics (and related) colloquia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.colorado.edu/physics/academics/graduate-students/graduate-course-schedule&quot;&gt;PHYS comps 1 courses and electives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;table&gt;
      &lt;thead&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;PHYS&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;course&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;/thead&gt;
      &lt;tbody&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5030&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Math Methods 1&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5040&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Math Methods 2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5210&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Mechanics&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;7230&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Stat Mech 1&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5250&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;QM 1&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;5260&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;QM 2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;7310&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;EM 1&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;7320&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;EM 2&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;/tbody&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;non-academic-mentoring&quot;&gt;Non-academic mentoring&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Boulder area:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NCAR&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NIST&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NOAA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maths faculty occasionally work as consultants over the summer (e.g., in cryptography). During the academic year I am warned such applied involvement is rare. From September to May most faculty are grinding their noses into books (else &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/strava-heat-map-military-bases-fitness-trackers-privacy/&quot;&gt;tracking rides on strava&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summer-employment&quot;&gt;Summer employment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few options:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;teach (8 weeks)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;REU (8 weeks)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;outside internship
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;e.g., &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.colorado.edu/physics/nist-prep&quot;&gt;NIST-PREP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;maths-pillar-sequences&quot;&gt;Maths pillar sequences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My initial and (after much deliberation, revision, and subsequent vacillation) final course load for Fall 2018 is comprised of 3 pillar courses at the 6000-level&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Algebra 1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Analysis 1&lt;/del&gt; (took SOML for credit instead)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Topology 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did have to read around other university’s departmental webpages to settle my decision for what courses to take as a 1st year graduate student. Here’s the digest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cu-boulder&quot;&gt;CU Boulder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer! This advice is relevant to the 2018-19 academic year, and, etc., the reader should contact the department for up-to-date and authoritative guidance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;http://math.colorado.edu/~kstange/&quot;&gt;Kate Stange&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Your main task in your first couple years is the required courses and prelim exams.  There are three main fall/spring sequences offered each year:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;algebra 1 &amp;amp; 2&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;analysis 1 &amp;amp; 2&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;topology &amp;amp; geometry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;and one additional requirement:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;complex analysis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Each sequence has an associated prelim exam, but you needn’t worry about those until you’ve completed the sequence in most cases.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Your usual course load would be 15 credits, which is 5 courses over the year.  You can do (3 fall / 2 spring) or (2 fall / 3 spring).  I usually recommend taking 2/3, since in fall you’ll still be getting your sea legs. (You can also take 3/3 with your tuition credit – beyond that I think you have to start paying more.)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The normal thing to do would be to take two pillar sequences.  These courses are heavy loads (think of one pillar course as two regular courses in terms of workload hours).  Electives will generally be lighter loads, and in spring you might choose an elective.  However, you might want a fall elective if something particular interests you (3/2).&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I would go with whatever is most comfortable/familiar to begin.  If you are an algebra type, start with the algebra, etc.  You can also register for all 3 and then perhaps drop one after a week or two.  You can also attend one you aren’t registered for for a while, just to see (just mention it to the instructor).&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;So, in short, my recommendation is to pick two of the three courses listed above, and you will also take Math 5905, our one-credit teaching course.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;As far as electives go, just a note:  cross-listed 5000/4000 level courses are sometimes aimed at undergraduates and graduate students from other departments.  Please ask the instructor if it’s appropriate for Math PhD students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;northwestern&quot;&gt;Northwestern&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside: Unlike UPenn 1st year students are not (generally) protected from teaching responsibilities. Such is the situation at CU Boulder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.northwestern.edu/graduate/handbook/teaching-policy.html&quot;&gt;“Teaching Policy: Department of Mathematics - Northwestern University”&lt;/a&gt;. Retrieved August 27, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Teaching experience is considered to be an integral part of the training of all graduate students, and is required each year of all students, with the exception of students in their final year of study.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;First-year students usually fulfill this requirement by assisting with grading. Upper-level students fulfill this requirement by serving as a teaching assistant for at least one course in an academic year.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The work of teaching assistants varies with the course and the faculty member who has primary responsibility but generally includes answering questions about homework problems in the recitation section (which meets weekly for each course), grading homework, and proctoring and grading quizzes, mid-terms, and final exams. The faculty member teaching the course makes specific arrangements with his/her teaching assistants concerning their duties. Recitation sections meet on Tuesday or Thursday; the lectures are on Monday, Wednesday and Friday, although there may be occasional departures from this model. Classes begin on the hour and last for 50 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.northwestern.edu/graduate/prelims/&quot;&gt;“Preliminary Examination: Department of Mathematics - Northwestern University”&lt;/a&gt;. Retrieved August 27, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;All students must pass the Preliminary Examination in order to continue with the program.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The Preliminary Examination consists of written examinations in the following three subjects: algebra, analysis, and geometry/topology.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Incoming students are invited and encouraged to take the Preliminary Examination upon entrance. There is no penalty for failing to pass a preliminary examination taken upon entrance to the program.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Incoming students will be required to take the first-year course in each of the prelim subjects they do not pass upon entrance, unless they submit documentation of having passed a comparable course at another institution (or other compelling evidence of familiarity with a subject).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The Preliminary Examination is given during New Student Week in September and at the end of the academic year (typically June).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Graduate students must take the Preliminary Examination in all three subjects by the end of their first academic year. Students who do not pass the Preliminary Examination by the end of their first year must pass a make-up examination in September of their second year in order to continue in the program beyond the first quarter of the second year. In the presence of strong evidence of other mathematical accomplishment, this rule may be modified or waived with the approval of the Graduate Committee.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;An award is offered at the end of each academic year to the student who has achieved the best performance in the Preliminary Examination. The award is accompanied by a monetary prize.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;upenn&quot;&gt;UPenn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.upenn.edu/graduate/yearbyyear&quot;&gt;“Graduate Program Year-by-Year, Department of Mathematics”&lt;/a&gt;. Retrieved August 27, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Fully-supported Ph.D. students ordinarily receive a fellowship in their first year, during which they have no teaching responsibilities and may take four courses.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Upon arrival in the Ph.D. program, new students take the Masters Preliminary Exam on key undergraduate mathematics; this serves as a placement exam. Those who pass the exam ordinarily take the beginning Ph.D. level courses in algebra (Math 602/603), analysis (Math 608/609), geometry-topology (Math 600/601), and an elective. (Exception: Those who enter with a more advanced background have an opportunity to place out of the beginning courses, and instead to move on to more advanced courses.)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Those students who do not pass the Masters Preliminary Exam upon arrival will ordinarily take the Masters Proseminar (Math 504/505), and possibly one or more of the masters level courses in algebra (Math 502/503), analysis (Math 509/509), and geometry-topology (Math 500/501), instead of the corresponding 600-level courses. These students need to pass the prelim by the end of their first year, to demonstrate their ability to move on to more advanced material.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Students whose native language is not English need to demonstrate their ability to communicate in English, during their first year. Those who cannot do so satisfactorily upon entry will take a special course in their first semester, designed to help them improve their English communication skills.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;In addition to attending their courses, first year students are encouraged to attend the Math Department Colloquium, where mathematicians from other universities speak on topics of general mathematical interest, and also the Friday Pizza Seminar, where grad students give the talks and only grad students attend (and during which the Math Department provides pizza and drinks).&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Typically first year students spend most of the following summer at Penn, and receive an additional fellowship stipend from the Math Department (with no teaching responsibilities) to enable them to pursue further studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tripos-part-iii-casm&quot;&gt;Tripos Part III (CASM)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part III of the Cambridge Mathematical Tripos sets some of the “most most selective” standards for passage into research level mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s quite possible to reverse engineer a 1st year PhD course load by isolating Part III courses of interest, then seeking out their Part I and II prerequisites. See particularly the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.maths.cam.ac.uk/undergrad/course/schedules.pdf&quot;&gt;Schedules&lt;/a&gt; and Form of Examinations for the Mathematical Tripos from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.maths.cam.ac.uk/undergrad/course&quot;&gt;“Undergraduate Mathematics: Course Information”&lt;/a&gt;. September 23, 2015.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hyping myself up with &lt;em&gt;high&lt;/em&gt; ambition by imagining that I am just finishing &lt;del&gt;Part II&lt;/del&gt; Part I, more realistically, and preparing to enter &lt;del&gt;Part III&lt;/del&gt; Part II, I think it’s feasible for me to alight on the goal of &lt;del&gt;finishing each of CU Boulder’s preliminary exams with an unconditional pass&lt;/del&gt; passing the prelim exams in 1 year, and completing the pillar courses in 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, the motivation is there. Why race through the preliminary exams? “Because it may come in useful later.” Who knew?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some (more) ambitious commentary from Körner’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dpmms.cam.ac.uk/~twk/PartIII.pdf&quot;&gt;unofficial guide to Part III&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most people who come to do Part III enjoy it (not all the time, it is very hard course) and are glad they came. However, each year we get a some students who discover that Part III is not at all what they expected or want. Here are some points that you may wish to bear in mind. Purpose We view Part III as a preparation for a PhD. If you are only interested in doing another year of mathematics you may well find the course too intense and too specialised. The answer to ‘Why are we doing this’ will often be ‘Because it may come in useful when you are doing research’.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I said earlier that it does not matter if you do not know a particular theorem or fact which your lecturer makes use of since the lecturer will be happy to help. It does, however, matter if you do not have the same kind of background as the rest of your class. The Cambridge students in your class will have followed courses whose syllabuses (and examination papers for the last few years) are given on the Faculty web site. Typically, they will have good control over all the courses in Part 1A, all the appropriate courses in Part 1B (that is the pure courses for pure students and the applied course for the applied students) and about six course in Part II. Thus, for example, if you attend a course in Quantum Mechanics the Cambridge students may have done 56 hours of courses. If you have done 40 hours and different topics you will probably still have the kind of general background required but, if you have only done one course of 24 hours, then the gap may be too great.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The lecturer’s Part III syllabus will often give prerequisites in sufficient detail to enable you to see whether you can tackle them. Frequently these show that some undergraduate course is not required. For example, there are undergraduate courses in General Relativity and Differential Geometry but the corresponding Part III courses often start from scratch. You should, however, expect such course to go quite fast and some general preliminary reading would be useful.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Most people are prepared to accept that Part III is a very hard course and that they will have to work very hard once it starts. It is also helpful to work quite hard before it starts. It is a good idea to discuss the Part III courses you intend to take with your present professors and ask their advice on preliminary reading. If you have a choice of final year courses, choose the ones which are most appropriate for your future plans.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Look at the old Cambridge Part II papers in the topics you intend to pursue and work through some of the questions. (Note that you are not preparing for an exam. Do the questions slowly, consulting the appropriate textbooks and thinking about the questions after you have done them.) If, in spite of your good intentions, you find that you are not doing as much as you should, remember that some preparation is better than none and persevere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More from Professor Körner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A […] psychological point.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Let me recall a well known story.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One evening, about the time when bananas were first being imported in Britain, Lord Leconfield was dining in his stately home with a friend. His guest observed that nobody really knew how good a banana could be unless he had tasted one straight off the tree.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Lord Leconfield said nothing at the time, but next morning he sent for his head gardener. ‘Go’, he told him tersely, ‘to Kew. Find out how to grow a banana. Come back here and grow one.’&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Off went the head gardener. A special greenhouse was constructed. The banana tree was splendid. Lord Leconfield took a lively interest in in its progress until it fructified. ‘I will have the banana for dinner tonight,’ he said as soon as the banana was ripe. And so he did — amid a deadly hush. The head gardener himself was there, concealed behind a screen.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The banana was brought in on a splendid dish. Lord Leconfield peeled it with a golden knife. He then cut a sliver off and, with a golden fork, put it in his mouth and carefully tasted it. Whereupon he flung dish, plate, knife, fork and banana on to the floor and shouted ‘Oh God, it tastes like any other damn banana!’ Banana tree and all were ordered to be destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The Cambridge Mathematics Departments are just mathematics departments like any other damn mathematics departments. If you did not enjoy the course at your previous institution you will probably not enjoy the course&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;applying-for-an-nsf-graduate-fellowship&quot;&gt;Applying for an NSF graduate fellowship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again from Prof Stange&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I just wanted to add a little info about the NSF GRF opportunity.  I encourage students to consider applying (I suggest speaking to your faculty mentor about this).  It is a great honour to receive one and would be valuable in terms of extra research time and flexibility (it would replace teaching as a funding source, and allow travel).&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Students who apply must be citizens or permanent residents.  Generally, students can apply only once after they begin their PhD work, either the fall of their first or second year.  The deadline is in mid October, and you need to have 3 letter writers and transcripts organized well before this.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Even more important, you need to submit a research plan.  You can deviate from this plan later (it isn’t a contract) but it should give specific problems and specific tools to attack those problems.  Therefore, you almost certainly need a faculty member to help you write the research plan.  This is the main obstacle, but also an opportunity to get to know a potential advisor.  As I said, it doesn’t have to be the faculty member you eventually do your thesis with, but it will give you an opportunity to explore possible avenues of research.  The exercise itself is valuable even if the application is not successful.  I encourage faculty to be open to helping with such applications.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Note:  This program is multi-disciplinary, and the design fits well in lab sciences where you have an advisor/topic early.  It doesn’t fit the usual mathematical graduate program where students choose an advisor/subject only several years into the program.  The upside is NSF doesn’t get as many mathematics applications for this reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;attend STEMinar, Physics colloquium, StatOptML seminar&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;pitch proposals in algebraic topology&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;presenting own ideas&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;asking for open problems&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;application tips&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;to explain the problem/impact&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;lie out tools to be used in the approach&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notetaking&quot;&gt;Notetaking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mpacers&lt;/code&gt;’s gusto and tactile sensibility in choosing to treat his preparations for Berkeley’s qualifying exams as experimental science, and log reading responses in a collection of 19 field notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;https://mpacer.org/explaining-this-collection/&quot;&gt;“Explaining this collection”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Knowing myself, I knew that I would be more motivated by the idea of producing something that is of potential worth for others than I would be by the mere prospect of perfunctorily checking a bureaucrats’ box. However important it may be, filling forms, checking those boxes has never been a particularly appealing prospect.My secret assumption has always been that everyone agrees with me (even the stuffy bureaucrats), but that others are better able to see past the grid into which they are placing themselves to the real purpose of whatever exercise is being conducted. I make the assumption of my own myopathy before I assume that the world truly revels in forcing people to do things that have a tenuous relation to what matters in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5415d6d6e4b09de883251c2f/541faed5e4b0ff88564851a0/541fb487e4b09194f7694010/1411363991191/Splitting+the+cost+of+thought+47.png?format=750w&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5415d6d6e4b09de883251c2f/542105a7e4b042b085c88779/542124ece4b0462bd0f5b7b3/1411458298501/Cracken+the+Hull+03.png?format=750w&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following their lead (and knowing how much I like notetaking by hand), I purchased a portable duplexing scanner (50-page capacity) to drop my notes into at the end of each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.samaltman.com/productivity&quot;&gt;“Productivity”&lt;/a&gt;. Sam Altman. Retrieved August 27, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I prefer lists written down on paper.  It’s easy to add and remove tasks.  I can access them during meetings without feeling rude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/coltongrainger/dotfiles/blob/master/.local/bin/scripts/one-sided-scan.sh&quot;&gt;one-sided-scan.sh&lt;/a&gt; and a corresponding two sided option to handle the scanning and chronological sorting of notes.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:ape&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:ape&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:ape&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If I’m going to ape Pacer, I want the records to &lt;em&gt;look good&lt;/em&gt; after the fact. I decided on monochrome scans at 300dpi, be named by their ISO date. &lt;del&gt;I have &lt;a href=&quot;https://tmsu.org&quot;&gt;TMSU&lt;/a&gt; if I really want to tag the files.&lt;/del&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:ape&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Colton Grainger</name></author><summary type="html">A survey of curriculum for first year PhD students in the maths department at CU Boulder, looking at cousin disciplines (applied maths, physics, computer science) and other universities.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Three Self-Introductions</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/three-self-intros" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Three Self-Introductions" /><published>2018-07-28T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-07-28T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/three-self-intros</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/three-self-intros">&lt;p&gt;After a contemplative and absurdly open-ended summer, I wrote three descriptions of myself and my goals for folks who I might look for mentorship from. Given their positive feedback, I’m posting my initial outbound emails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first message was intended for the maths department at CU, the second was a cursory message sent to the programming languages mentoring workshop (Stephanie Weirich had solicited applications on twitter), and the third was sort of a long-overdue thank you card to Issa Rice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cu-boulder-maths-dept&quot;&gt;CU Boulder maths dept&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(1) what are your goals for graduate school&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I aim to make novel contributions to the field of applied algebraic topology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon completion of a PhD, I want to be a researcher for a university, governmental agency, or non-profit organization. I would like to work in a English- or German-speaking metropolitan area that’s dense enough to have its own subway/rail system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, I am glowingly glad to be coming to a community of mathematicians and exact scientists at CU Boulder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;what particular challenges do you foresee for yourself?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do look up to academics who published early and often in their research careers (Jean Yang, Matt Might, Scott Aaronson, Philip Guo, among others). I think I’ve chosen such prolific role models in compensation for my attending a liberal arts college in rural Idaho, from which I graduated in 2016 feeling provincial and green.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I anticipate I will be challenged to pace my ambition—especially what I have imported from wildly successful academics—against the reality that algebraic topology has a very long build-up to research level publication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plmwicfp-2018-travel-scholarship-application&quot;&gt;PLMW@ICFP 2018 travel scholarship application&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please briefly describe any research or technical projects that you have worked on or plan to work on.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My research interest is in applied algebraic topology, specifically topological data analysis (TDA). I aim to implement a natural type-system for TDA such that (i) a TDA workflow can be composed of strongly typed functional programs, (ii) details of each program’s implementation can be hidden when reasoning in an algebraic context, (iii) each program can be type-checked (assuring modularity) and, if possible, mechanically verified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a first year PhD student, I have yet to formally take an advisor; however, Prof Agnès Beaudry’s research on Computational Chromatic Homotopy Theory (DMS-1612020/1725563) is the clear (and significantly deeper) semantic dual to the syntax I hope to employ when implementing a type system for TDA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(In terms of my preparedness to understand the workshop: I have a familiarity with Haskell, Scheme, and typed lambda calculus from recent independent study. I have experience with category theory from my undergrad. I have a naive appreciation of homotopy type theory.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why would you like to attend PLMW@ICFP?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first two years of my PhD, I want to structure iterative paper submissions on a tractable project in TDA. While my intended audience includes algebraic topologists, category theorists, and type theorists, I believe that type theorists (and the PL community at large) are the most approachable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Great PR. As publicity chair for POPL 2018, Jean Yang recorded and posted interviews from a broad cross-section of PL researchers, with the explicit purpose of “conveying to the potential new members of the POPL community … what POPL is about.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;GitHub. The “constellation of artifacts” accompanying PL research is largely showcased in public git repositories, together with commit histories, issue threads, and pull requests.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No absurd entry barriers. In his POPL interview, Xavier Leroy mentioned “I was admitted in ENS, Ecole Normale Supérieure in Paris, which is the church of French mathematics. I really wanted to do math. Then, I found out that math was more difficult than I thought. Their courses were really hard and they didn’t make them very accessible. They wanted to find the next Fields Medalist.” I think the attitude is different in the PL community, where initial contributions need not be world-class.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in summary, I hope to attend PLMW@ICFP because I believe the PL community is approachable, and I want to get a sense of the tools I would use and of the realistic goals I should set for myself to produce a type-system for TDA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lastly, I want to hear Weirich and Polikarpova speak, as they are both role models to me, and I admire their work (in hs-to-coq and Enforcing Information Flow Policies, respectively).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cold-email-to-issa-rice&quot;&gt;Cold email to Issa Rice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have kept abreast of your &lt;a href=&quot;https://issarice.com/content-creation&quot;&gt;content creation&lt;/a&gt; since last September, and I wanted to say thanks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for holding up a light to demonstrate what an open notebook is and can do&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for references to gwern, Aaron Swartz, and Vipul Naik&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for writing that hauls, tows, and tracks beginners (like myself) through the intermediate steppes of establishing a canonical online identity, finding a voice, finding a project, etc.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:observe&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:observe&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I studied maths/physics through undergrad (and will return to grad school this fall), but for the last two years I’ve done service work: a year in medical case management at a refugee resettlement agency in Houston, and a year at a homeless shelter in Olympia. I am motivated by your writing to become a stronger programmer, and to find a niche in which I have comparative advantage to do the most good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to setup a database for my friend at the resettlement agency (something like mnemosyne, but instead of flash cards, it displays a short English language health bio for clients who otherwise have limited English proficiency), and I’m wondering if you could point me to (sort of introductory) examples where you’ve used mySQL&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:mysql&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:mysql&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; or SQLite.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:sqlite&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:sqlite&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:observe&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I notice I tend to especially stiffen up and turn verbose when I’m first talking to people. It can get over the top. Like, I wanted to reference Bulgakov’s &lt;em&gt;The Master and Margarita&lt;/em&gt; to compare some &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Miscellany_for_deletion/User:Riceissa/Animal_Charity_Evaluators&quot;&gt;drama&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Conflict_of_interest/Noticeboard/Archive_113#Vipul.27s_paid_editing_enterprise&quot;&gt;WP:COIN&lt;/a&gt; to Pilate’s deliberations and decision to turn Yeshua Ha-Nozri to the Sanhedrin. But really. It’s a cold first email. I have to draw the line at literary references likening the involved parties to mythomorphic divine figures.]&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:observe&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:mysql&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Issa kindly replied, “For MySQL, maybe going back in the commit history of one of my projects would be easiest, e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/riceissa/aiwatch/tree/41956844f204cd01f0e9bf401774ce62bea03104/sql&quot;&gt;https://github.com/riceissa/aiwatch/tree/41956844f204cd01f0e9bf401774ce62bea03104/sql&lt;/a&gt; shows a fairly minimal setup. (The downside is I can’t guarantee there aren’t any syntax errors for arbitrary commits in the history.)”&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:mysql&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:sqlite&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“For SQLite I think I’ve only used it for one project. You can find the schema for that at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/riceissa/wikidossier/blob/master/schema.sql&quot;&gt;https://github.com/riceissa/wikidossier/blob/master/schema.sql&lt;/a&gt; and insertion stuff at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/riceissa/wikidossier/blob/f477b6b2f9e0448d20a27bdc54e817d21f64b18d/wikidossier.py#L79-L101&quot;&gt;https://github.com/riceissa/wikidossier/blob/f477b6b2f9e0448d20a27bdc54e817d21f64b18d/wikidossier.py#L79-L101&lt;/a&gt; The tutorial I used while making that is &lt;a href=&quot;http://flask.pocoo.org/docs/1.0/tutorial/&quot;&gt;http://flask.pocoo.org/docs/1.0/tutorial/&lt;/a&gt;.”&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:sqlite&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Colton Grainger</name></author><summary type="html">After a contemplative and absurdly open-ended summer, I wrote three descriptions of myself and my goals for folks who I might look for mentorship from. Given their positive feedback, I’m posting my initial outbound emails.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Folks I Look up to</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/see-also" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Folks I Look up to" /><published>2018-07-04T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-07-04T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/see-also</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/see-also">&lt;p&gt;Few of my ideas are original, especially those dealing with the material design
and organization of this site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for style sheets, existential motivation, and technical HOWTOs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pgbovine.net/&quot;&gt;Philip Guo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://matt.might.net/&quot;&gt;Matt Might&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://issarice.com&quot;&gt;Issa Rice&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Much credit to Issa Rice for forging a really crisp style sheet. (I even
use a variant of the headers when taking notes by hand.) I’ve pulled
multiple features from his site: headers, CC0 licensing, and general
modus operandi.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for encouragement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://vihart.com/vi-hart-faq/&quot;&gt;Vi Hart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.evelyneastmond.com/&quot;&gt;Evelyn Eastmon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.ncase.me/&quot;&gt;Nikki Case&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for feedback on tone, voice, and &lt;em&gt;making human&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wolfgang_Iser&quot;&gt;Iser’s&lt;/a&gt; implied reader:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collegeofidaho.edu/directory/david-rosoff&quot;&gt;Dave R.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collegeofidaho.edu/directory/megan-dixon&quot;&gt;Megan D.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collegeofidaho.edu/directory/eric-spencer&quot;&gt;Eric S.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collegeofidaho.edu/directory/steve-maughan&quot;&gt;Steve M.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give credit for the idea to create &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;quamash.net&lt;/code&gt;^[The domain name refers to &lt;em&gt;Cammassia quamash&lt;/em&gt;, e.g., from the OED, 1814 &lt;em&gt;Lewis &amp;amp; Clarke’s Exp.&lt;/em&gt; The Chopunnish are now dispersed in villages…for the purpose of collecting quamash.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;W. Caleb McDaniel’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.wcaleb.rice.edu/&quot;&gt;academic wiki&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Joachim Breitner’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://mitschriebwiki.nomeata.de/&quot;&gt;MitScriebWiki&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Issa Rice’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://issarice.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;Updates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michael Pacer’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://mpacer.org/qualifying-exam-materials/#/qualifying-exam-written-portion/&quot;&gt;Qualifying Exam Materials&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michael Goerz’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://michaelgoerz.net/studies/&quot;&gt;Studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://learning.subwiki.org&quot;&gt;https://learning.subwiki.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Colton Grainger</name></author><summary type="html">Few of my ideas are original, especially those dealing with the material design and organization of this site.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Personal Information Management</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/pim" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Personal Information Management" /><published>2018-05-27T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-05-27T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/pim</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/pim">&lt;p&gt;These quotes are taken from William Jones and Jaime Teevan’s, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washington.edu/uwpress/search/books/JONPEP.html&quot;&gt;Personal Information Management&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a (large, outdated) mind-map
&lt;img src=&quot;http://blog.coltongrainger.com/attached/20180611-personal-information-management.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the quotes I found useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p. 3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;PIM is both the practice and the study of the activities people perform to acquire, organize, maintain, retrieve, use, and control the distribution of information items such as documents (paper-based and digital), Web pages, and email messages for everyday use to complete tasks (work-related and not) and to fulfill a person’s various roles (as parent, employee, friend, member of the community, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p. 13&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In rough equivalence to the input-storage-output breakdown of actions associated with a PSI, essential PIM activities can then be grouped as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Finding/re-finding activities move from need to information. These activities affect the output of information from a PSI.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Keeping activities move from information to need. These activities affect the input of information into a PSI.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Meta-level activities focus on the PSI itself and on the management and organization of the PICs within. Efforts to “get organized” in a physical office, for example, are one kind of meta-level activity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p. 18&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Finally, there is sometimes discussion of personal knowledge management (PKM). Given the usual ordering of data &amp;lt; information &amp;lt; knowledge, one is tempted to think that PKM is more important than PIM and, ultimately, this may be so. One major challenge of PKM, however, just as with knowledge management more generally, is that the articulation of rules and “lessons of a lifetime” in a form that we (and possibly others) can understand. Knowledge expressed and written down becomes one or more items of information—to be managed like other information items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p. 26&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Another reason orienteering may be preferred is that it can provide both an overview of the information space being searched as well as context about where the desired information is located in that space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;recognizing&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;recalling&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p. 27&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Malone (1983) noted that spatial location helps support the finding of physical information. Similarly, the location of a piece of digital information is a particularly important type of context used when orienteering for personal information (Teevan et al. 2004).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p. 39&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Information keeping (or just keeping). Decision making and actions relating to the information item currently under consideration that impact the likelihood that the item will be found again later. Decisions can range from: (1) “ignore, this has no relevance to me”; (2) “ignore, I can get back to this later” (by asking a friend, searching the Web, or some other act of finding) to purposive seeking of information as a consequence of a need to satisfy some goal; and/or (3) “keep this in a special place or way so that I can be sure to use this information later”.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Information organizing (or just organizing). Decision making and actions relating to the selection and implementation of a scheme of organization and representation for a collection of information items. Decisions can include: (1) How should items in this collection be named? (2) What set of properties make sense for and help to distinguish the items in this collection? (3) How should items within this collection be grouped? Into piles or folders?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p. 40&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Information maintaining (or just maintaining). All decisions and actions relating to the composition and preservation of a personal information collection. Decisions involve what kind of new items go into a collection, how information in the collection is stored (Where? In what formats? In what kind of storage? Backed up how?), and when do older items leave the collection (e.g., when are they deleted or archived?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p. 42&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Keeping decisions often occur in a gray area where determination of costs, reciprocal benefits and outcome likelihoods is not straightforward (Jones 2004). In the logic of signal detection, this middle area presents people with a “damned if you do; damned if you don’t” choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p. 43&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Both options—filing and piling—have their advantages and disadvantages. Filing information items—whether paper documents, e-documents, or email messages—correctly into the right [directories] is a cognitively difficult and error prone activity. Difficult arises in part because the definition or purpose of a [directory] is often unclear from the label (e.g., “stuff”), and then may change in significant ways over time. Determining a [directories] definition may be at least as problematic as determining a categories definition. Worse, people may not even recall the [directories] they have created and so create new [directories] to meet the same or similar purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p. 46&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The fragmentation of information across forms also poses problems in the study of PIM. There is a natural tendency to focus on one form of information in order to mange the scope of inquiry—to study only email, for example, of the use of Web bookmarks, or the organization of paper documents. But a focus by the information form can have the effect of endorsing current application-centric partitions of information and the information fragmentation that results from these partitions—certainly on of the most vexing problems in PIM today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p. 50&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;People are hampered in their efforts to organize information by a lack of adequate system support for basic features (such as ordering or the reuse of structure) and by a lack of support for the integrative use of a single organization for different forms of information (e.g., e-documents, email, Web references, informal notes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p. 54&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How should a person’s information be organized? Or can people effectively keep information for later use and repeated reuse without bothering much about information organization? For some people in some situations, the answer may be that organization is not that important.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;But for other people, in other situations, their own intelligent efforts to structure and organize information are critical to the creation of supporting &lt;em&gt;external representations&lt;/em&gt; of a project of problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For example, the right diagram can allow one to make inferences more quickly (Larkin &amp;amp; Simon 1987). The way information is externally represented can produce huge differences in a person’s ability to use this information in short-duration, problem-solving exercises (Kotovsky, Hayes, &amp;amp; Simon 1985). Different kinds of representations, like matrices and hierarchies, are useful in different types of problems (Cheng 2002; Novick 1990; Novick, Hurley &amp;amp; Frances 1999).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p. 84&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To support the researcher’s role as primary data collection instrument, Chatman (1992), advocates that researchers maintain three types of notebooks: (1) a field diary for recording observational notes, the “simple reporting of phenomena”, which is used, as part of triangulation, for testing criterion validity; (2) method notes, which consists of “strategies employed or that might be employed to obtain data”, and thus record observation and ideas about the usefulness of certain methodologies, their effects, and how they may be changed for future research; and (3) a theory notebook for “testing construct validity and the generation of propositional statements to explain phenomena”, which is used as part of theory building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p. 85&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The analytic technique of “memoing” begins at the outset of data collection through recording certain observations and ideas in the theory notebook. Later, as data analysis progresses, these theory notes are rewritten in the form of extensive memos that connect the researcher’s thoughts on different phenomena and are later used as part of theory building, for which emphasis is placed on identifying negative cases or anomalies that refute any theoretical framework established for the investigation. Miles and Huberman (1992, p. 72) cite Glaser and Strauss’s (1967) definition of memoing, which is a classic: “the theorizing write up of ideas about codes and their relationships as they strike the analyst while coding … it can be a sentence, a paragraph, or a few pages … it exhausts the analysts momentary ideation based on data with perhaps a little conceptual elaboration”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p. 110&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ontology. Attempt to formulate an exhaustive and rigorous conceptual schema within a given domain. Often an ontology is a hierarchical data structure containing all the relevant entities and their relationships and rules (theorems, regulations) within that domain (Wikipedia 2006).&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Taxonomies. Hierarchical structures for classifying a set of objects. They are less expressive than ontologies as a means for expressing structure on objects in the world. They only allow subclass relationships, and cannot represent relationships between concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Thesaurus. A data structure designed for indexing, where we associate with every important term in the domain a set of terms related to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p. 116&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Among the many and diverse issues existing in [digital libraries] research, ranging from intellectual rights management to user collaboration to architectural interoperability, the most relevant from a PIM point of view are issues related to the management of metadata (and more generally with the so-called semantic interoperability) and the various types of multimedia data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p. 131&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Metadata treats information as opaque, but offers a standard model for talking &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; those objects in assorted ways. Examples include grouping (as in file directories), annotating (as in ID3 tags for media and del.icio.us for Web pages), and linking (as in the World Wide Web)… much information management relies only on object metadata, [and] so can be supported over data objects of all types.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p. 140&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While a metadata scheme can ignore the complex formats of the objects it is talking about, there must still be a common API for talking about those objects. In particular, any metadata scheme needs some standard way to indicate &lt;em&gt;which&lt;/em&gt; object is being talked about. This may be a standard scheme for &lt;em&gt;naming&lt;/em&gt; objects (e.g., file names or URLs) so that their names can be used to [reference] them, or it might be accomplished by &lt;em&gt;embedding&lt;/em&gt; the metadata with the object being annotated (as with ID3 tags in media files).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p. 155&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In defense of “flat hierarchies”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As Malone and others have pointed out, a physical filing structure is a hierarchical category structure (Jones, Phuwanartnurak, Gill &amp;amp; Bruce 2005; Malone 1983). Putting an object into a tree structure is a process that is exquisitely sensitive to choices made while descending the hierarchy. An error made in choosing the category can result in a object being very far from its “correct” file location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p. 171&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dabbish et al. present a more systematic analysis of message types. Messages could serve multiple functions, but the overall breakdown was Action requests (36%), Information requests (18%), Information attachments (36%), Status updates for projects/tasks (21%), Scheduling requests/responses to scheduling requests (14%), Reminders for meetings/actions (16%), Social mesages (8%), and Other (12%).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Finally, there have been video studies of how people allocate time processing email (Bellotti et al. 2005):&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;54% composing mesages&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;23% reading messages, attachments, and links&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;10% filing messages&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;6% scanning inbox messages for things to read or deal with&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;2% deleting messages&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;2% looking for messages in folders&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;2% managing attachments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Colton Grainger</name></author><summary type="html">These quotes are taken from William Jones and Jaime Teevan’s, Personal Information Management, 2007.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What I Want on my Android</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/android" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What I Want on my Android" /><published>2018-05-19T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-05-19T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/android</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/android">&lt;p&gt;What do I want on my phone?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;music&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;podcasts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mnemosyne&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Now that I think about it, my phone &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be a little mirror of the reading / lectures on my laptop. If I hammer out the music updating workflow, then it’d make no difference to ship over the pdfs as well.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The naming convention is (sort of) &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;%y-%b-%n-%a-%t&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;YEAR-ALBUM-TRACK-ARTIST-TITLE.EXT
2015-NumericalMethods-01-LyudmylaBarannyk-MATH428SP15SESSION1.mp4
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mounting-and-unmounting&quot;&gt;mounting and unmounting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mkdir ~/android_mount&lt;/code&gt; (if needed)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;connect by USB&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jmtpfs ~/android_mount&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;file operations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fusermount -u ~/android_mount&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.debian.org/mtp&quot;&gt;Don’t use sudo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;see-also&quot;&gt;see also&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pgbovine.net/PG-Podcast-32-Tergel.htm&quot;&gt;“Philip Guo - PG Podcast - Episode 32 - Tergel on building mindful relationships with technology”&lt;/a&gt;. Retrieved August 10, 2018.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;http://tergel.com/tagged/phones#_=_&quot;&gt;Tergel’s phone exhibit&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://78.media.tumblr.com/9599aa4530df8966116e2954508a3d28/tumblr_o69jitCTo51qenaaio1_500.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;tiny sculpture of concerned woman holding two phones&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://78.media.tumblr.com/dbad003049a1263ed4d96df1961aed39/tumblr_o69jnv8uxL1qenaaio1_500.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;flower vase with checking its phone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Colton Grainger</name></author><summary type="html">What do I want on my phone?</summary></entry></feed>